<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two fruitfull exercises the one: A Christian discourse vpon the 16. and 17. verses of the 16. chapter of the booke of Iudges, wherin are handled these three principal heads: The portreature of Dalila. The bridle of lust. The seale of secrets. The other: A godly meditation vpon the 41. and 42. verses of the 10. chapter of Saint Luke, containing especially The profit of repreoofe, togither with the necessitie and excellencie of Gods word. Also a brief discourse intituled A buckler against a Spanish brag: Written vpon the first rumor of the intended inuasion, and now not altogither ynmeete to be published. By E.R.</title>
            <author>E. R., fl. 1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10289</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848197</idno>
  <idno type="VID">13276</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240892296</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 20571</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S112956</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99848197e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10289)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1639:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two fruitfull exercises the one: A Christian discourse vpon the 16. and 17. verses of the 16. chapter of the booke of Iudges, wherin are handled these three principal heads: The portreature of Dalila. The bridle of lust. The seale of secrets. The other: A godly meditation vpon the 41. and 42. verses of the 10. chapter of Saint Luke, containing especially The profit of repreoofe, togither with the necessitie and excellencie of Gods word. Also a brief discourse intituled A buckler against a Spanish brag: Written vpon the first rumor of the intended inuasion, and now not altogither ynmeete to be published. By E.R.</title>
                  <author>E. R., fl. 1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Eliot's Court Press] Impensis G. Bishop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Recto of final page contains list of errata.</note>
                  <note>Sig. F8r is a separate title page, reading: A Godlie meditation vpon the 41.42 verses of the 10.chapter of S. Lukes Gospell, containing especially the profit of reproofe, togither with the necessitie and excellencie of the word of God. Londini, Impensis G. Bishop. 1588.</note>
                  <note>Sig. K5r is a separate title page, reading: A briefe discourse intituled A Buckler against a Spanish brag: Written vpon the first rumor of the intended inuasion, and now not altogither vnmeet to be published. 1588.</note>
                  <note>Some pages closely cropped.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Delilah --  (Biblical figure) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible --  O.T. --  Judges XVI, 16-17 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible --  N.T. --  Luke X, 41-42 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13276:1"/>
            <p> Two fruitfull exercises, The one: A Christian <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course vpon the</hi> 16. <hi>and</hi> 17. verses of the 16. Chapter of the booke of Iudges, wherin are handled these three principal heads:</p>
            <list>
               <item>The portreature of Dalila.</item>
               <item>The bridle of Lust.</item>
               <item>The sea;le of Secrets.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>The other: A godly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> vpon the 41. and 42. verses of the 10. chapter of Saint Luke, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining especially</p>
            <list>
               <item>The profit of reproofe,</item>
               <item>Togither with the necessitie and excellencie of Gods word.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Also a briefe discourse intituled A Buckler against a Spanish brag:</hi> Written vpon the first rumor of the intended inuasion, and now not altogither vnmeete to be published.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By E. R.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDINI, Impensis G. Bishop.</p>
            <p>1588</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:13276:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13276:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="poem">
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13276:3"/>
                     <l>Of women, here you may behold, the best, and woorst:</l>
                     <l>MARIE the best, but DALILA, the most accurst;</l>
                     <l>MARTHA, nor best, nor woorst, a meane twixt both doth keepe,</l>
                     <l>Like slumbring heads, that neither wake, nor soundly sleepe:</l>
                     <l>But she that doth to MARIES place, and praise aspire;</l>
                     <l>Must haue of MARIES godly choise, a like desire.</l>
                     <l>A MARGARET there is, well knowne, in woorth, in name,</l>
                     <l>Whose Christian vertues do deserue, a MARIES fame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I flatter not, my words are true:</l>
                     <l>MOMVS doth know, it is hir due.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull, and right Vertuous Ladie, the Ladie M. P. <hi>E. R. wisheth the full measure</hi> of all tèmporall and <hi>spirituall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Madam, it hath not proceeded of anie vndutifull forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, that I haue not before this time testified my most dutiful deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards your Ladiship. No man can cary a more thankful remēbrance of your great kindnes and vndeserued bounties; and indeede it is the onelie thing I am able to perform. These poore exercises presume not to supplie this want of better abilitie, onely they come vnto your La. to present you with a little scantlin of the greatnes of my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful affection, and desire to accomplish some grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things more woorthie of your most Christian vertues. It may please your La. to accept of them: a better measure of knowledge may haply bring foorth more acceptable matter heerafter. If this pamphlet shall content your La. I hope others to whose view I haue in respect of my bounden dutie towards you made the same subiect, will not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiously censure my poor endeuors, but giue them such construction as I am willing to deserue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I cannot performe that which I earnestly desire. And thus I commend your good La. to the mercifull protection of the Almightie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your La. most humbly to command, <hi>E. R.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:4"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:5"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>GOod Reader, some dutifull respects, not any desire to be in Print, haue mooued me to publish these exercises. I must confesse that it is an enterprise at this time, beside my profession, and therfore do the more earnestly craue thy fauorable acceptation, which must proceed of thy kind disposition not of my desert. I make this sute especially to the better aduanced in the studies of Diuinitie, whom me thinks I heare to say: Sowter to thy slipper; If they and the rest shall do me this fauour: it will incourage me to imploy my small talent with better profite heerafter; otherwise as I shall be hartily sory that I did not expresse my bounden dutie to that vertuous Ladie in some other action, so from hencefoorth I will content: my selfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and presume to displease no man else with my simple en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuors. This let me likewise craue, and obtaine of thee, that thou wilt impute the imperfections which thou shalt find in this pamphlet, to my long discontinuance in good studies, &amp; to the want of those helps wherewith I might haue better polished the same. The Carpenter may roughly hew with his axe, but cānot carue without some finer tooles: the Smith may fashion with his hammer, but cannot make his worke smooth &amp; seemely without his files, and yet bad is the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manship that fitteth not some place. The countrymans eie that hath not seene the deckings and ornaments of Courtlie pallaces, contents himselfe with the sight of bare wals; and to those whose mouths are not acquainted with delicacies, grosser meats neuer seem vnsauery: To such I hope these my poore exercises will be acceptable in honest simplicitie: and to the rest, in friendly curtesie. Farewell.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13276:5"/>
                  <head>A Christian discourse vpon the 16. and 17. verses of the 16. <hi>Chapter of the booke of</hi> IVDGES.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Iudg. 16. vers. 16. 17.</bibl>
                        <p>And bicause she was importunate vpon him with hir words continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and vexed him, his soule was pained vnto the death.</p>
                        <p>Therfore he told hir al his hart, &amp;c.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The portreature of Dalila.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese words offer vnto vs in generall a double conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; The one, the importunitie of <hi>Dalila;</hi> the other the frailtie of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:</hi> and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar many good lessons are of ech part to be learned, which I will gather and set downe, as shall be best agreable with the order and method which I intend to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue in this discourse. <hi>Dalila,</hi> as appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Iudges. 16. ve. 6. 10. 13.</note> in the processe of this Chapter, had giuen the assault vnto <hi>Samson</hi> three seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times, and now at the last hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the conquest. Where first note
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13276:6"/> without any farther preambles, that whē the wicked haue once gotten the lest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in vs, they begin to plead full pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session, when they haue obtained some smal power and authoritie, they become insolent, and tyrannising ouer our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, seeke with them the destruction and ruine of our soules, wherein no labor, no endeuor, no pollicie, no pretence wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. <hi>Dalila</hi> is not faint to bring hir pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose to passe, <hi>Dalila</hi> dallieth, but delai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to discouer the secrets of <hi>Samsons</hi> hart, she speaketh faire, she vrgeth him with vnkindnes, she coniureth him, euen as he tendereth hir loue to deale plainly with hir in that high point of his strēgth, so much hurtfull to hir friends the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins: she seeth that <hi>Samson</hi> was far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged vnto hir, that she had brought him wholie to hir lure, that he had yeelded himselfe to hir deuotion, and therefore presumed that he woulde rather grant hir any thing, than hazard the losse of hir loue; vpon which perswasion it may be coniectured, that she framed this, or the like speech vnto him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Samson,</hi> my best friend, to whom I haue wholy deuoted my selfe: the protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13276:6"/> of thy vnfained affection towards me are great and manie, and I haue in some measure tasted the same in effect: yet this shall be a more certaine, and vndoubted testimonie thereof, if thou wilt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to grant but this one thing which thou hast so often denied. Thou perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest great, and almost incredible things by thy strength: no enemie is able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide thy force: a poore iawe bone suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <note place="margin">Iudg. 15.</note> to ouercome thousands; thy hand, to rent Lions; thy shoulders, to beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">Chap. 14 Chap. 16</note> the strong gates of walled cities. This strength cannot proceed of thy sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of thy greatnes, or of anie other externall thing, wherin many of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listins do match thee in euery respect; it must needs be that some inward vertue, and more diuine spirit doth assist thee in the accomplishment of so strange and great actions: therfore I pray thee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate this secret vnto me, tell me wherein thy strength consisteth. Thou knowest what interest thou hast in my best affection: thou hast no reason to suspect that I will discouer the same, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so inward with thee in other secrets: try me that am vnto thee as thy selfe, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13276:7"/> as my self do vnfainedly loue thee, Good <hi>Samson</hi> let me obtaine this fauor, which will be vnto me the greatest obligation and pledge of thy good will which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto thou hast giuen, or euer shalt giue heerafter, the deniall whereof will mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister vnto me iust cause to thinke that thou hast not that affiance in my fidelity, which my hartiest deuotion hath beene alwaies most willing &amp; ready to deserue: nay if thou shalt refuse me in this small request, hauing thereby so good assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the confirmation of my loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, and of the concealing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with all faithfull secrecie; then fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well loue, farewell affection, farewel <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> and impute not this breach to any want of good will in thy sweetest <hi>Dalila,</hi> but to the small curtesie and kindnes which I haue found at thy hands in this my earnest sute. This or the like speech, tempered with more pathetical and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible arguments, you may imagine to haue proceeded from hir, which proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be termed <hi>Dalilas</hi> charme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with she bewitched and besotted <hi>Samson.</hi> Wherin may be obserued the nature and propertie of this kinde of women, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13276:7"/> make their members, but especially their toongs, as it were baits and instruments, to entrap those whom they perceiue any whit inclined to their lasciuious conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation. And although it be onely expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the text, that <hi>Dalila</hi> was importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate vpon <hi>Samson</hi> with hir words: yet Salomon hath a more full description of hir behauiour and disposition, in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chapter of his Prouerbes, where <note place="margin">Prou. 7. 6<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> 8. 9. 10. &amp;<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> hir importunitie is more fully bewraied vnto vs. To the end therefore that we may the better looke into hir, and hir wanton practises; it shall not be amisse to drawe some counterfet of <hi>Dalila,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not in liuely colours, nor abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in euery part, yet agreable with that which Salomon in his said Chapter, and in some other places briefly proposeth vnto vs. Let not perfecter painters blame my workmanship, if they shall find that I begin not this portreature with the part which the precepts of that art requireth, nor condemne my vnskilfulnes, if this <hi>Dalila</hi> shall want that perfection which shall be expected.</p>
                     <p>I will begin with that which although it be but an excrement, and the least and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13276:8"/> basest thing of the whole body, yet not in least estimation with <hi>Dalila,</hi> nor the least argument of a <hi>Dalila,</hi> I meane the haires of hir head, frizeled, frounced, broyded, spangled, and set out in mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous sort to the view of those that are disposed to gaze thereon. This surely is a token of great lightnes in <hi>Dalila,</hi> of pride in many, and an euident signe of vanitie in all that delight therin. By these haires, <hi>Samson</hi> lost his haire, and hauing lost his haire, he was bereaued of his eies, and not long after also of his life. These are the snakes of Medusas head, which tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the beholders thereof into stones. And trulie the senselesnes of <hi>Samson</hi> in this point, doth argue that <hi>Dalilas</hi> haires had wrought the same effect in him. For although they appeare beautifull, and pleasing in <hi>Samsons</hi> eie for a time, yet sting they incurably in the end, not like Medusas snakes, but rather like the sting of that beast, which bereaueth vs first of sense, and then of life. By these haires manie licentious youthes are somtimes no lesse besotted, than was Nero with the haires of his Poppea, who is said to haue worne them set in gold, and beset
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13276:8"/> with pretious pearles, whose example they also follow, wearing their mistres haire for a fauor in their hats, or in some other place about them, as a publike te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonie of the impudent incontinencie of the one, and incontinent impudencie of the other. But these dames forgetting Saint Peters rule, do easily forget all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie; <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 3.</note> and what should they not forget, that haue made shipwracke of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestie?</p>
                     <p>It were to be wished that some of the Deboras, and such like chaste, &amp; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise vnspotted matrones of our time, were not so much affected to fashions, that they might blush to bear this badge and marke of <hi>Dalila,</hi> wherein they must perforce accuse themselues of vanitie at the least, or else accuse Saint Peter to haue dealt too hardly with them in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribing that rule of decencie and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in this behalfe, who admitteth not the excuse of fashions which gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do ordinarily pretend, but doth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly cut off and reiect that monstrous spreading out of haire which is so rifely vsed of the most, &amp; that sometimes none of their owne: so as it may be affirmed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13276:9"/> that the making of perruques and such like toyes pertaining thereunto, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a verie profitable trade in manie parts of Christendome, and not least of all in England. Neither is that pretence and shift to be allowed of those, who thinke it a sufficient excuse, to say that they weare no other haire than their own, reserued from time to time for this purpose: but they must know, that as it best becommeth them to weare their own: so they are not to weare the same after their owne humour, but after the rule prescribed, and set downe in the word. The pretence of nobilitie or gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie in this excesse, is fleshlie, and no sufficient priuilege for any of whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer qualitie, for that toleration in this case is onelie current, which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alloweth. And we see, that the word is so far from tolerating the immodest frizeling and spreading out of haire in <note place="margin">Pet. 3. 3.</note> anie; as it expreslie forbiddeth it in all. I will not denie, but that as a comelie vse of al other attires is to be allowed in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; so the haire also may be vsed in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and orderlie sort, as the best dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed matrones, who are not addicted to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13276:9"/> fashions, do weare the same: but that it should be laid out in such vncomely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as the compasse and greatnes of the haire, should exceede the compasse and greatnes of the whole head and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; seemeth not only monstrous, but also repugnant to al Christian modestie. The prerogatiue of gentlewomen exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to greater and richer things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the difference of their estates, and degrees may better be discerned; and the greater honor and reputation will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their dignities, of the best dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; the farther they shall remooue this badge of <hi>Dalila</hi> from them. Which if they shall refuse to do, it may iustly be feared, that the Lord will without delay put in execution against the daughters of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the sentence of his prophet Esay, long sithence pronounced against the daughters of Sion, <hi>and will make their heads</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Isai. 3. 17. 18. 19. &amp;c.</note>
                        <hi>bald, and take away the ornament of the slippers and the calls, and the round tiers, the sweete bals and the bracelets, and the bonnets, the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the head, and the flops, and the head bands, and the tablets, and the eare-rings, the rings and the mufflers, the costly apparell, and the vailes and the wimples, and crisping pins,</hi>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13276:10"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13276:10"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13276:11"/>
                        <hi>and the glasses, and the fine linnen, &amp; the hoods, and the launes, and in stead of sweete sauors there shall be stincke, and in steade of a girdle, a rent, and in stead of dressing the haire, baldnes, and in steade of a stomacher, a girding of sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and burning in stead of beautie.</hi> I haue beene somwhat the more curious in this trifle, bicause it is a thing wherin women are most curious, and I hope I shall seem the lesse tedious, bicause idle huswiues do spende so much time in decking and laieng out of this excrement. Thus are the verie haires of <hi>Dalila</hi> importunate.</p>
                     <p>I come next to hir forehead, where may be noted the very picture of impudencie and shamelesnes it selfe, whatsoeuer she speaketh, she blusheth not; whatsoeuer she doth, she changeth not colour; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer is obiected against hir, she altereth no whit hir countenance; and no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, for <hi>Quae semel verecundiae limites tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siliuit, eam bene &amp; gnauiter impudentem esse oportet:</hi> She that hath once passed the bounds of shamefastnes, must needs euer after be shameles. Why then should <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lila</hi> blush? Nay rather why should she not be bold, and set a good face on the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? This lesson needeth not to be taught
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13276:11"/> them, they haue it at their fingers ends, and is so well practised of all <hi>Dalilas,</hi> as they dare with greater boldnes intrude themselues into the company of the best disposed matrones, the better therby to couer the blemishes, and blots of their name. These shameles foreheads dare to attempt any thing, bicause they feare not to betray them selues by their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. It is very true, that the face wherein there is any sparke of modesty, is easily stained, when the conscience feeling it selfe guilty of the least crime, is burthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therewith; and so is content to giue sentence against it selfe, euen with silence, according to the saying of the Poet:</p>
                     <q>Heu quàm difficile est crimen non prodere vultu:</q>
                     <q>
                        <l>O what a hard, and graceles thing it is,</l>
                        <l>Not for to blush when one hath done amisse.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>But the forehead of <hi>Dalila</hi> is so sliked and polished with impudencie, as being charged with any fault, yea although she be almost conuicted therof, yet carrieth the matter away with the boldnes of hir countenance, and sheweth not the least suspition of guiltines in hir forehead. If <hi>Dalila</hi> had not been notablie impudent,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13276:12"/> she could not but haue blushed to solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite <hi>Samson</hi> so often to bewray a secret of that importaunce, or rather she might haue feared, that hauing once missed of hir purpose, he would haue smelled out hir diuelish and pernicious intention: but she had as litle shame as honesty, and <hi>Samson</hi> as little sight, as vnderstanding, and being blind by loue, was also berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that true iudgement &amp; discretion, whereby he might easily haue discerned hir suttelties by hir forehead. Thus is the forehead of <hi>Dalila</hi> also importunate.</p>
                     <p>Let vs come one step lower, to the eies, being the place, as French Salust writeth, where Cupide hideth himselfe, and the gates whereby lust entereth. But the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eie is the certaine note of an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant and light minde, and you shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer see a <hi>Dalila</hi> without this note, for this is also a principall baite wherewith she taketh fooles, and hir wanton lookes, are so many hookes, whereby the simple are intangled. Herewith she is able to giue signification of hir lasciuious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, although hir toong be silent, he needeth no other broker that is disposed to bargin with hir. By this glasse you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13276:12"/> may looke into the secrets of hir hart, and take a view of hir wanton dispositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereof Demosthenes that famous Orator, hath long sithens giuen vs ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertisement by this sentence: <hi>Oculi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum indices:</hi> The eies bewray the maners.</p>
                     <p>And the scripture hath also discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs in diuers places the poyson <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 2. and 39. 7.</note> which proceedeth from hence, whereof it hath giuen vs admonition to take heed, and forbidden vs in expres termes <note place="margin">Eccl. 9. 5. 7. 8. &amp; 42. 12. Mat. 5. 28.</note> not to gaze vpon women. The Basilisque as we read, infecteth and killeth by a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret corruption, issuing from his eie: and <hi>Dalila</hi> like the Basilisque, by like infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, seaseth first on our affection, and then priuilie scattereth hir poison into the better part, to the destruction (without repentance) of body and soule. But this difference is betweene <hi>Dalilas</hi> eie, and the eie of the Basilisque, that the poison of the one is not to be auoided, bicause it infecteth the very aire; the other is void of such contagion, if we can moderate our affections, and turne away our faces from hir wanton lookes. For although Potiphars wife did cast hir eies vpon Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph, <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 7. 10.</note> and daily sollicite him to commit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13276:13"/> wickednes with hir, yet Ioseph by the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of Gods spirit, was able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand hir lasciuious temptations, and to stop his eares against hir alluring and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tising prouocations. This ought euerie good Christian to performe in like as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saultes, and with Ioseph to avoide the <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 12.</note> company of Potiphars wife, and with Iob <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 1.</note> to make a couenant with his eies, and with Dauid to praie to the Lord, that it <note place="margin">Psa. 119. 37.</note> wil please him to turn away his eies from regarding of vanitie. It is recorded of a certaine Philosopher, that finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe subiect to manifold temptations by reason of his eies, he was not afraide to pluck them out; bicause of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all conflict which he felt in his hart by occasion thereof, but especially in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of fleshly desiers, whereunto by the frailty of his nature he was inclined: and this he esteemed to be a present remedy, to take away the cause whereby his wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton appetite was stirred vp. But this mans action wanteth a great part of that cōmendation which otherwise it would haue deserued, if offering no violence to the members of his bodie, giuen by God to good vses, he would rather haue mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13276:13"/> and brideled his affections. And yet this man liuing in blindnes, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the true knowledge, shall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse the wanton and licentious impes of our age, who are so far from turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their eies from <hi>Dalila,</hi> that they feed their fancies, and nourish their affections euen with hir lookes, hauing eies full of adulterie, as it is in the second Chapter <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. 14.</note> of Saint Peters second Epistle. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we find this precept in the scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that if our eie offende vs, we should <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 29.</note> plucke it out, and cast it from vs: yet is it not ment in the iudgement of the best learned, that we shoulde depriue our selues of that member, but that we shuld moderate, tame, and cut off that affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which causeth our eie thus to offend, for otherwise the verbal and literal sense alloweth the Philosophers action before alleaged, and some other like tragicall and bloodie executions, done by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then men, for some good respects, vpon their owne bodies.</p>
                     <p>Among other passions which <hi>Dalila</hi> is woont most liuely to expresse with hir eies, this is one, that she is able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand teares at all times, in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13276:14"/> as a signification of some great sorrow conceiued, if she see that it may be a meane to mooue some commisera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in him, for whom she laieth hir nets, and so thereby to obtaine hir purpose. But these teares are full of deceit, and are powred into thy bosome to ouerwhelme thy bodie with infinite miseries, and to plunge thy soule also in perpetuall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If the Crocodile weepe: take heed, he intendeth to deuour thee: and if <hi>Dalila</hi> powre out teares; auoide hir snare, or else thy destruction is neere. She hath no more mercie than a Crocodile, for how can she haue any cōpassion, that is void of all true loue, and carieth deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to nothing else, than to the satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of hir lust, and maintaining of hir brauerie, by thy beggerie: wherein the crocodile may seeme to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hir, bicause the nature of this beast being rauenous, it is credible that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger enforceth him to this butcherie: but <hi>Dalila</hi> being full, hath neuer enough, she will not be satisfied, but like the horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leach cleaueth close to the skin, vntill it be ready to breake: and yet in this the horseleach also goeth before hir; in that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13276:14"/> it sucketh nothing else, but the corrupt blood, and bad humours of grosse bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: but <hi>Dalila</hi> sucketh out the best blood, euen our hart blood, and he esca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth well whose purse onelie paieth for hir pride. Therefore be wise to follow the counsell of Salomon in the sixt of his Prouerbes, <hi>Desire not hir beautie in thy hart,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 25. 26.</note>
                        <hi>neither let hir take thee with hir eie lids, for bicause of the whoorish woman a man is brought to a morsell of bread, and a woman wil hunt for the precious life of a man.</hi> Thus are the eies of <hi>Dalila</hi> also importunate.</p>
                     <p>The nose may not be ouerpassed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out some note. For this she prouideth hir sweete sauours and perfumes, wherewith she may not onely please hirselfe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so those that haue accesse vnto hir. Hir muskes and hir ciuets, to what purpose serue they? to perfume hir daintie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strels: hir pomanders and hir powders, wherefore are they prouided? to delight hir daintie nostrels: hir flowers, and hir posies of all sorts, to what ende are they worne? to refresh hir daintie nostrels, and that she may be traced by the sent of those odours. And no maruell, for some of these daintie <hi>Dalilas</hi> would hardlie
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13276:15"/> abide the sauour of their owne corrupt bodies, if these other hot smels were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued: a reason why they are so much in vse with them, and that of chaste ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, verie few or none, do follow their example, bicause of the suspicion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto these perfumes are subiect, not that it is vnlawfull or vnseemely, for gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women of qualitie to weare them, but for that they are vnwilling to beare the note which ordinarilie accompanieth these smels. This being now a daies a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cōmon speech in everie mans mouth: A woman then sauoreth best, when she smelleth of nothing. And Salomon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other notes of that light huswife, described in his prouerbs, maketh hir to vse this speech to the yoong man desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of vnderstanding: <hi>I haue perfumed my</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. 7. 17. 18.</note>
                        <hi>bed with myrrhe, aloes, and cynamon: Come let vs take our fill of loue vntill the morning.</hi> Thus is the nose also of <hi>Dalila</hi> importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
                     <p>The eares of <hi>Dalila</hi> are of like force, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies open to hearken if there be any fit for hir humour, and inquisitiue, where, and howe, she may best spred hir net to entangle them, and it is the best comfort
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13276:15"/> that can arriue, when any news is broght vnto hir that a foole is taken. It is in vaine to talke to hir of modestie, of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, of temperance, chastitie, and such like vertues, which are the principall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments beseeming a woman, she liketh not such discourses: but wanton songs, idle and prophane communication, full of all kinde of incontinent and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate termes, do best delight hir eares. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that serueth to effeminate the minde, as musicke without measure (for with measure it is not to be disallowed) soundeth sweetely in hir eares; herewith she lulleth hir peramours a sleepe, and so charmeth them, that although they are waking, yet sleepe they stil on the bed of wantonnes and securitie. Psalmes and Hymnes are banished the place where she resideth, such a consort is not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with hir disposition, it will wake the children a sleepe, and so indeed it wil, she is not deceiued. I remember to haue read, that those which are stoong with a certaine worme called (if my memorie faile me not) Tarantula, are cast as it were into a dead slumber, by the force of the poyson, which admitteth no other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13276:16"/> remedie, than the sweet notes of musick, whereby the partie stoong is presentlie cured. And although there be manie other good preseruatiues against <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> poyson; yet is there none more force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to awaken vs out of the dead slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whereinto she shall haue cast vs, than Psalmes, and Hymnes to our good God, which may serue as a counterpoyson to <hi>Dalilas</hi> inchaunting musicke. But to adde a little better grace to this little part, <hi>Dalila</hi> is also content to endure some pain, and to haue hir eare pearced, that some rich iewell or other ornament may be hanged thereat, to serue in steede of a baite, or lure to drawe the bad dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vnto hir, according to that practise of Cleopatra, who by the like addition to hir other lures, may seeme not onelie to haue intised Antonius the rather to visite hir: but had also at all times a rich morsell in readines, to saue hir wager, when hir table should not be furnished with other chates, answerable to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayture. Thus are the eares also of <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> importunate.</p>
                     <p>The cheekes of <hi>Dalila,</hi> (whatsoeuer hir naturall complexion is) are red for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13276:16"/> the most part, not with blushing, for she hath not so much grace, but with pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and colouring. The other parts likewise of hir countenance though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps naturally crow-white, yet by art are made lilly-white, and there is such a correspondencie betweene the colours, as if you should not iudge hir to be some Hellen, you should offer hir great iniury. If you breath vpon hir face, you hazard hir fauor, bicause you alter hir fauor, or rather make hir ill fauored. The Sunne may not shine, the winde may not blow, the raine may not drop vpon hir cheeks: and why? the purenes of hir painted complexion will not abide it. I haue heard it cited out of an ancient and graue writer, who asketh this question of the painted dames of his time, with what face they durst thus to colour their faces? Their faces giuen vnto them by GOD, their faces made according to the perfection of his workmanship, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, absolute, and without all controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to adde to that by art, which no art was able to make, much lesse to correct or amend: so as he maruelled how they could imagine God would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13276:17"/> them for his workemanship, at the last day, hauing so much disguised, and altered them selues, from that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor and complexion, which it had pleased him in their creation to bestow vpon them. A perfect Painter, Caruer, or other like artificer, hauing drawen a portrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or carued an image, is able to iudge, and to know his owne worke, so long as it remaineth in the state wherein he first made it: but if a bungler, or some sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple grinder of colors, shall slubber ouer the same with new shadowes, new deuises; how is it possible for that Painter, after some few yeeres, to know the picture? But God who searcheth the raines, and looketh into the most secret corners of our harts, is able to know these <hi>Dalilas,</hi> but will not acknowledge them to be his, who forgetting them selues and their duties towards their maker, are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with that naturall color, which in his diuine iudgement seemed best for them. Thus are the cheeks, and color of <hi>Dalilas</hi> whole countenance also impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate.</p>
                     <p>We are now come to that part which is of greatest force, and whereby <hi>Samson</hi>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13276:17"/> was especially forced to vtter the secrets of his hart vnto <hi>Dalila,</hi> viz. hir mouth with the appurtenances, which being the principall instrument touched in the text, and described more at large by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon; it shall be meete to enter into a more particular consideration, of the dangerous effects which it worketh, and of the manifold dangers, whereunto it maketh men subiect. We had in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this discourse an imaginarie forme of speech which might seeme to haue beene vttered by <hi>Dalila</hi> vnto <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> wherein I easily beleeue, that I haue not set foorth the one halfe of that grace, of that earnestnes, of that sweetenes, of those amorous gestures, affections, and passions, which it is likely <hi>Dalila</hi> expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed. In the processe of this historie, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peereth, in the first place, that she dealt with him in the kindest termes she could, <hi>Tell me I pray thee.</hi> In the next, she tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. verse 6.</note> hir speech with an vnkinde expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulation: <hi>See, thou hast mocked me, and told me lies,</hi> and yet once againe she <note place="margin">Verse 10.</note> praieth. In the third place, she praieth him no more, but taketh a more round course; <hi>Hitherto thou hast beguiled me, and</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verse 13.</note>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13276:18"/>
                        <hi>told me lies, tell me how thou maist be bound.</hi> At the last she becommeth impatient, and entreth into termes of passion. <hi>How</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verse 15.</note>
                        <hi>canst thou say I loue thee, and thy hart is not with me?</hi> Besides, it is added that she is importunate, and importunate continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <note place="margin">Verse 16.</note> and vexed <hi>Samsons</hi> soul to the death. Thus we see how bad women can play the good orators, and plead their causes with great cunning. If one way will not serue, another shall be found out; if sweete words alone will not preuaile, then let some sower expostulation be added: if both will doo no good, then more passionate termes, and coniurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may take effect. And thus, with this kinde of charme was <hi>Samsons</hi> mind dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, as appeareth in the text, that his foule was pained vnto the death, such force had hir words, such deepe impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion did hir importunate intreaties make in his hart. If he be but a common friend, nay a stranger vnto vs, that with kinde and louing speeches craueth our assistance, and fauor in any reasonable cause; we should thinke our selues void of common humanitie, if we should not condescend to his petition; but much
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13276:18"/> more would we condemne our selues, of more than inhumanitie, if we should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie a request of some importance to the partie towards whom we carry an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie affection. And therefore it is no maruel if <hi>Samson</hi> were thus perplexed, whose hart was wholy in <hi>Dalilas</hi> possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather, (such was his infirmitie) in hir hart.</p>
                     <p>Vnder sweete honie sometimes lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth much poison, and vnder fawning words, is hidden no lesse deceit, and he swalloweth a deadly hooke, that taketh not good heede to this baite. There is no treacherie more dangerous, then that which is masked with a shew of amitie: and words, are so manie swords, vnlesse the hart and toong doo concurre togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the one vtter truly, that which the other meaneth sincerely. We cannot looke into this part; it is the onely office and property of the Lord, to see the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets which lurke therein, and therefore it falleth out, that so many are deceiued by the trust which they repose in the treacherous. The Phisition to make his bitter pils the more acceptable to his patient, wrappeth them in sugar, and by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13276:19"/> that meane beguiling his tast, the pils are the more willingly receiued: so they that intend mischiefe in their harts, will like cunning Phisitions, make such a confection, as their words shall seeme more sweete than hony, whereby they will the more easily effect their wicked purposes. But the Phisitions pollicy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the tender care he hath of the health of his patient, whose stomack without some helpe will not brooke the bitternes of the medecine: but treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Dalila,</hi> applieth hir flattering spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to no other end, than to snare him towards whom she pretendeth loue, and to compasse hir wicked deuises more freely without suspition. But the poore bird is soonest deceiued, when she giueth eare to the foulers call: and the seely fish that taketh the bait, receiueth therewith also his bane. If Argus harken to Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curies pipe, Argus hundred eies will soone be ouertaken with sleepe, and Mercuries swoord readie to cut Argus throate. The Syrens songs are sweete but deceitfull, and they them selues are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else then the images of so manie <hi>Dalilas,</hi> Maidens vpward, and of great
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13276:19"/> beautie, but monsters vnder the water, and like ouglie fishes: faire in shewe, and sweete in shewe, but in deede foule, most bitter, and rauenous creatures. That which is faire in them, is set foorth to the view, to allure: but their deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are hidden, least they should deter: and therefore Vlisses like a wise and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet man, is said to haue stopped his eares at their songs, and to haue caused him selfe to be bound to the mast of his ship, thereby to avoid their alluring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations and enchanting songs, like <note place="margin">Psa. 58. 4. 5.</note> vnto the Adder, which stoppeth hir eares, and refuseth to heare the voice of the charmer, charme he neuer so wisely. We are by nature credulous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore easily induced to beleeue pleasing speeches: we are also by nature corrupt and vitious, and therefore apt to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace pleasing things. But let vs make this profit of this poeticall fable, that we neither beleeue rashly intising words, nor embrace foolishly delightfull vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but to stop our eares against <hi>Dalilas</hi> perswasions, and if she be in deede a <hi>Dalila,</hi> aswell to distrust, as to denie hir flattering requests.</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13276:20"/>
                     <p> That olde suttle Lion, of whom we read in Aesops fables, had (no doubt) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured manie beasts, which partlie of pittie, partlie by intreatie visited him in the time of his dissembled sickenes; but the foxe was not so easily inuited to his bloodie caue, he had craft enough to looke into the lions deceit, and looked before he lept, he sawe manie steps lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the den, but none comming from thence, and therefore wisely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew his foote at the first entrance: so ought we to take heed, that <hi>Dalilas</hi> faire speeches allure vs not to hir den; from whence being once entred, it is as harde to finde passage, as it was for the small beasts to escape the lion, or for those poore wretches who wandring in <hi>Daeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> Labyrinth, were soone deuoured of the hungry Minotaure. It is easie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue one that wanteth experience and iudgement, but he that is godlie wise, wil way circumstances, and consider manie things before he giue credite to smooth speeches, viz. what the partie is that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureth, what is required of hir, how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, and expedient to be granted, and what may be the issue and euent of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13276:20"/> the same. This if <hi>Samson</hi> had thought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he would neuer haue yeelded to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilas</hi> temptations, how sweete soeuer hir requests were, or how sower soeuer hir expostulations, for he might thus haue reasoned with himselfe, vpon those cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances: what is this <hi>Dalila?</hi> A har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot; what is a harlot? an inconstant and light huswife, of an vnsetled affection, as apt to entertaine any other, as my selfe; of whose loue I cannot promise vnto my selfe any assurance, and therefore why should I trust hir? Againe, she is a Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine, or at the least a fauourer of them: they are mine enimies, and seeke my life: she hath now thrise practised to trie my strength, &amp; she is yet stil instant, in what case had I been if I had told hir the truth at the first, and if the Philistines had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed been at hand to set vpon me? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why should I trust hir? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose should she be thus inquisitiue to know this secret? It can profit hir little, if indeed she loue me, and it may much hurt mee, if she dissemble, nay whether she loue or dissemble, it may be manie waies preiudiciall vnto me. Therfore why should I trust hir? She is a woman, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13276:21"/> weake, she may be corrupted with gifts, intreated with promises, compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with threats to reueale the same: nay she may be made an instrument to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue me of this hidden vertue, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not trust hir. If <hi>Samson</hi> had thus resolued; he might haue saued his haire, his eies, his life, to many good ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, for the aduancement of gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But <hi>Dalila</hi> seeing the aduantage which she had gotten by his credulitie, yeeldeth not an inche, but is rather the more importunate. She giueth not ouer at the first repulse, nor despaireth at the second, but presseth him with all earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the third and fourth time, <hi>tell me, tell me, tell me, tell me.</hi> Wherin we may obserue the great diligence of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their enterprises, and how the hope of successe at the last, mooueth them to attend the same with patience. It was a greater conquest to ouercome <hi>Samson,</hi> than all the Philistins were able to performe, and therefore besides the glory of the victorie the expectation of reward might somewhat mooue hir to put in execution hir desseins by al possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes. This she was sure of at the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13276:21"/> least, to please those that had set hir a worke: and this (no doubt) was a spur to set hir forward in hir treacherous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and not to desist vntill the end. This might teach the godly disposed this good lesson, to vse like diligence in their better resolutions, and not to faint or to be dismaid, when their endeuors haue not presently their wished effect: and withall to consider, by what means they may deliuer <hi>Samson</hi> from the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of <hi>Dalila,</hi> and saue not onely his haire, but also his head and soule from destruction. But as we are very impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in the expectation of good things: so are we no lesse slacke in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of these good offices towards our brethren: the one, a note of distrust and diffidence in Gods goodnes: the other a signe of small charitie and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the straying sheepe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the successe of our actions, answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for the most part, vnto our hope, bicause the same is carnal, and respecteth onely the satisfieng of our owne wants, and not the setting foorth of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and benefit of our neighbor. The like example of patience, and earnest expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13276:22"/> of successe in hir amorous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, is to be seene in Iosephs mistris, who is said in Scripture to haue tempted <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 10.</note> and prouoked him daily; but she wanted <hi>Dalilas</hi> force to perswade, bicause Ioseph had more grace than <hi>Samson</hi> to resist, but this is certaine, that she wanted no good will to compasse hir wanton sute. But that Iosephs mistris is so diligent, <hi>Dalila</hi> so earnest, and both so patient, in their wicked enterprises, may be the lesse woondred at, bicause their father the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, spared not to giue our Sauior Christ three seuerall assaults, and would not giue ouer vntil Christ had said vnto him: <hi>Auoid Sathan.</hi> Which teacheth vs, that if <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 10.</note> we looke to escape the danger of the temptations of the diuell, and his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, (of which traine <hi>Dalila</hi> is a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officer) we must not harken to their sweete woords and allurements; whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the diuell cast before vs, we must not snatch at the baite, whatsoeuer his carnall members promise and profer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, we must not accept therof, though he saie: <hi>All these will I giue thee,</hi> that is, <hi>all</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Verse 9.</note>
                        <hi>the kingdomes of the world, and the glorie of them:</hi> though they offer to giue vs full
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13276:22"/> possession of their bodies, and all that is theirs: yet shall it be good for vs to su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect them, their gifts, &amp; whatsoeuer else proceedeth from them, for you shall find that all tendeth to mischiefe. If you open Pandoras boxe, you shall finde it full of all kind of miseries: though Pallas giue hir wit, Venus beautie, Mercurie craft and eloquence to perswade Epimethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us: though hir boxe be neuer so costly, never so curiouslie wrought, yet when Epimetheus hath opened it, hee shall finde therein most fearefull things; yea he will wish he had neuer touched the same.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>Dalila</hi> doth not onely gloze with hir toong, but close also with hir lips: which propertie we find set foorth in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons Prouerbs, in these words; <hi>So she caught him, and kissed him.</hi> But although <note place="margin">Prou. 7. 13</note> Iudas kisse his master, it is not for anie deuotion or affection towards him, but rather a note of his treacherous resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to betraie him: though Iudas saie; <hi>Haile master,</hi> and intertaine him with <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 48.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Mar. 14. 45.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 47.</note> like speeches of dutie, yet is it but a watch word, whereby he hath concluded to giue significatiō to the Iewish blood-suckers
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13276:23"/> to apprehend him. But <hi>Dalila</hi> is noted in the saide place to play a Iudas part not onely in this, but also in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of holines, as some haue obserued in these words: <hi>I haue peace offrings: This day I haue paide my vowes;</hi> so as it appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that the vilest and most vicious ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, maske their wicked actions with a shew of holines, and that they are loath to make their lothsome conuersation publikely knowen, howsoeuer they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute their bodies priuately at home: which kinde of hypocrisie, added vnto the ouglines of their other abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doth fill vp the measure of their sins, to their vtter confusion and destruction. Take heed therefore first of <hi>Dalilas</hi> allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring speeches; but in any case take heede that she do not catch thee; but especiallie take heede that she do not kisse thee. Thus is the mouth, lips, and toong also of <hi>Dalila,</hi> aboue all other parts importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
                     <p>By the whole countenance, you may giue more then gesse of the inward dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of the minde; <hi>Vultus index ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi:</hi> and that painter hath attained the principall point, that hath drawen the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13276:23"/> iust proportion of the face.</p>
                     <p>The armes, and hands of <hi>Dalila</hi> serue to manie purposes; they are in steede of hookes and bandes, to holde fast those whom they haue, or would intertaine: Iosephs mistris before alleaged, espieng fit opportunitie for hir purpose, (if Ioseph <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 12.</note> would also haue been at leysure) caught him by the garment: but Ioseph left the same in hir hand, and fled, he would not be taken. Whereof this lesson ariseth, that being brought into like straights, we should rather flee their wanton im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brasings with the losse of some smaller things, than yeeld our selues into their hands, to be reserued to great dangers. In the Prouerbs we find, that the honest woman there mentioned, <hi>Came foorth,</hi> and met hir foolish paramour, <hi>and caught</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Prou. 7. 13. 22.</note>
                        <hi>him:</hi> but he not so wise as Ioseph, <hi>followed hir, as an oxe that goeth to the slaughter, and as a foole to the stocks for correction:</hi> in which words, the butcherly crueltie of bad wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, is in some sort represented vnto vs. That <hi>Dalilas</hi> hands, are bands, the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher in his seuenth chapter affirmeth, and <hi>Dalila</hi> hir selfe, in this action also <note place="margin">Eccle. 7. 28.</note> confirmeth it. Now as he that is bound
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13276:24"/> is depriued of the free vse and libertie of those parts wherewith he should helpe himselfe: so he on whom she hath once laide hir handes, and whom she holdeth fast in hir armes, hath lost the libertie not onely of his bodie, which is at hir commandement; but also of his minde, wherein with hir, sathan chalengeth his part. But she hath yet another vse of hir hands; she can embrace <hi>Samson</hi> with the right hand, and pick his purse with the left; and when all is gone, thrust him out of the dores with both: A practise verie common with <hi>Dalila,</hi> and they are hir best guests that bring full bags: and the prodigall childe who careth little for his money, and is content to fill hir neuer full hands, is best welcome vnto hir. Thus are the armes and handes also of <hi>Dalila</hi> importunate.</p>
                     <p>In other things I will not be curious, bicause according to hir variable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constant minde, she changeth hir attire daily. This onelie note out of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Esaie, that <hi>Dalila</hi> is hautie, and wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Esaie 3. 16.</note> with a stretched-out necke; a signe of great pride: minseth as she goeth; an argument of as little chastitie: and tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13276:24"/> with hir feet; a token of no lesse va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. And if anie apparell can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be more lasciuious, more wanton than another, giue it to <hi>Dalila:</hi> the ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test is best for hir, and the vainest best beseemeth hir: for <hi>Dalila</hi> will be sure to weare the lightest and the vainest: vnlesse for a purpose she pretend some holines, for vnder the gowne somtimes is hidden much hypocrisie, and vnder the gowne lurketh also much contagion and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: much like vnto Mausolus tomb, and other statelie monuments of migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie princes, which carie a shew of great beautie in outward apparance, and are verie curiously carued, painted, and gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but within them is nothing els to be found, than a few rotten and putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bones.</p>
                     <p>Although I had Argus eies, or the quicknes of Linxes sight; yet were I not able to looke perfectly into the inward parts of <hi>Dalila,</hi> and to discouer all the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of hir hart, wherof this former dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course hath yeelded but a nigardly scant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin. And although I haue endeuored to draw hir whole counterfet in some rude colors, thereby in some sort to expresse
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13276:25"/> the force of hir importunity, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate practises: yet the whole is lesse than the foote: which if a skilfull pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter would take in hand, as he did, that drewe the picture of Hercules by the print of this onelie member: doubtles <hi>Dalila</hi> would be (as indeed she is) a most vglie monster. Thus is the picture which I vndertooke to drawe, according to my poore skill, finished: wherein with each outward part, I haue glaunced at <hi>Dalilas</hi> inwarde disposition, and described in briefe termes the maner of hir behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; adding such caueats by the way, as seemed fit for the place: although haply following some other order and method in this discourse, according to the course of the text, the notes which occur might haue beene better placed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The bridle of lust</head>
                     <p>NOW we haue considered of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilas</hi> importunitie, it remaineth that we looke also into <hi>Samsons</hi> frailtie. Where first it needeth not to seeme strange vnto anie, that <hi>Samson</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing so strong a man, should be ouercome of a woman: for this resistance required rather the inward force and vertue of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13276:25"/> the mind, than any bodily strength: <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> had ynough of the one, but by resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting the spirit, and yeelding to his flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appetite, seemeth to haue quenched and extinguished the other. Is it any maruel, if in a citie, castell, or other place hotlie assaulted, the conquest is easily gotten, when the captaine is content to betraie himselfe, and when the enimie is voluntarily admitted within the walls, and intertained in the towne with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; or when the captaine is loth to yeeld the fort, and yet will not betake himselfe to his weapons to repell the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie? This is the case of <hi>Samson; Dalila</hi> his enimie lieth in his bosome, and lust and concupiscence like a traitor lurketh in his bowels: so as within and without he feeleth a double assault. But the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren enimie is easily repelled, if the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesticall be strongly repressed: and this should haue beene <hi>Samsons</hi> first care, to bridle and temper his affections, which caried him with violence into these las<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious actions.</p>
                     <p>The lust of the flesh is an old rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious guest, intertained long sithens by our father Adam, and hath euer sithens
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13276:26"/> cleaued fast vnto vs, and will be as bold a tenant with our posteritie. He admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, and we must moderate it, for vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly expell it we cannot; will we, nill we, it will dwel in vs: but we must take heed, that it raigne not in vs; it is an insolent, and bloodie tirant, if it be once suffred to beare sway, and therefore the Apostle giueth vs this brotherly admonition, or rather in brotherly sort he praieth vs; <hi>To abstaine from fleshly lusts which fight against the soule.</hi> He saith not, which contend <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 11.</note> onelie, which striue, or which make anie light skirmish; but which fight, and as it were wage battell; and that not against the bodie, but against the soule. By figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, it appeereth that it is no white-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerd soldier, but a strong and stout cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and therefore it behoueth vs to arme our selues. By fighting against the soule, argueth his malice, and sheweth the danger wherein we are, if we make not strong resistance. The wounds of the bodie are oftetimes by the skill of expert Surgeons, curable, although the stroke be verie deepe: but the wounds of the soule admit no plaister, if once the enimie haue vs in his power. Satan is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13276:26"/> bloodie, and void of all compassion, and therefore will hold fast, and will not faile by a continuall suggestion of wicked lusts, lasciuious cogitations, and lewd actions, to wound the soule more deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he may bathe himselfe in our blood, and take full possession of this better part.</p>
                     <p>Now the fight is the more dangerous where the enimie is domesticall, and in the same bodie with vs: Lust is a dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall enimie, and by this occasion is priuie to all our resolutions, acquainted with our counsels, looketh into our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berations, and hath manie suttle coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers to minister matter, to preuent whatsoeuer shall be concluded by the spirit against it, and ceaseth not to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise to betraie our bodies to <hi>Dalila,</hi> and our soules to the diuel, and therefore the fight is dangerous; the resistance very hard. <hi>The spirit</hi> (saith our Sauior) <hi>is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 4<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                        <hi>but the flesh is weake:</hi> noting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence which the one obtaineth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the other. And S. Paul confesseth, that <hi>To will was present</hi> with him, but he <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> found no meanes in him to performe that which was good: whereby appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13276:27"/> that concupiscence and lust hath great force euen in the regenerate, and such whose names are entred into the booke of life.</p>
                     <p>But how shall this tameles colt be bridled and subdued? By no meane bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than by resisting the first temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: by cutting off the occasions, which allure vs to this sower-sweet sin. If <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> had auoided the first baite, it is likelie he had not swallowed the second: if he had not entred into the harlot at Azzah, <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>udg. 16. 1.</note> he would not so soone haue been taken with <hi>Dalila,</hi> for when God seeth that we forsake him; he also leaueth vs, and giueth vs ouer to our inordinate lusts: and as we haue shewed our selues rebels against so good a God: so they play the tyrants ouer our soules, and striue to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vs headlong to the pit of destruction. He is a bad soldier that yeeldeth at the first assault, naie he is a traitor that doth not defend the fort committed vnto him, euen to the death. Our fleshly lusts are heerin like the Crocodile, if we flie, they triumph: but if we persecute them, they yeeld, and are cooled: not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse them is dangerous; to giue them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13276:27"/> the least libertie, is to conspire with them; and wholie to yeeld, is as it were to cut our owne throats.</p>
                     <p>To giue place to one allurement, draweth on another, and sinne stealeth on secretly, and ouertaketh vs vnawares: it is like the snake which hauing gotten his head into any place, will easilie draw in his whole bodie. The corruption of our nature inuiteth vs to harken to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pleasing vanitie, and the weakenes of our nature is vnable, and our slacknes vnwilling, to denie our selues those de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights which the flesh desireth: but the aduersarie is both diligent to practise, and subtill to compasse his desseins, and hath great power also to put them in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. And therefore let this conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, (if nothing else) mooue vs to put on a ful resolution to resist the first temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. And we must not onely resist them at the first, but if we are so vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, that they once preuaile against vs, we must haue a godlie care to cut them off betimes, before they grow to farther strength: we may not foster and nourish them, which were as foolish a part, as if a man should make much of a dangerous
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13276:28"/> disease, and study as well by intemperate diet, as other riotous exercises, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and increase the same: as if a gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie man, should eate slimie and corrupt meats; or one subiect to the dropsie, should take in his cups freely, and as it were ouerwhelme his bodie with drink, without respect to the nature and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his disease, whereunto this strange diet is cleane contrarie. But we must ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vse all moderation; like vnto those who fauoring their health, do acquaint their bodies with temperate exercises, eate holesome meates, and rather vse meanes to preuent sicknes, than to make themselues subiect thereunto. I reade of a fish, that carrieth the name (and woorthily) of a sea foxe, who feeling him selfe deceiued by the fishermans baite; standeth still, striueth not with the hook; but taking hold of the line, byteth it in sunder, and is content to swallow it into his bowels, which being large inough to receiue the same, without farther dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; he deceiueth the fisherman, saueth his life and escapeth. This fish teacheth vs this good lesson, that although our fleshlie lust cause vs to swallow <hi>Dalilas</hi>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13276:28"/> hooke, yet finding into what danger we haue brought our selues therby, we must stande still, like the fish, that is, wee must not proceede any farther in our wantonnes: but we must cut off the line, that offereth this bait; that is, we must reiect <hi>Dalila:</hi> we must temper our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and rather swallow the hooke; that is, endure some small inconueniences, and so escape farther danger; than to giue hir leaue to strike the same into our throat, and so to hold vs in perpetuall slauerie, and bondage to hir wicked ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, to the hazard of our bodies and soules. But this is indeed a hard conflict, and the flesh will not patiently hearken thereunto, nor yeeld it selfe vnto the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the spirit, howsoeuer the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be apparant. Medea could see many inconueniences in hir matter of loue, with Iason, and she could confesse this much: <hi>Video meliora, probóque:</hi> but hir car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affections would not suffer hir to follow that good way, which onely natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reason (for she was a heathen) shewed vnto hir. We are in the same predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Medea, and our fault is much greater than hirs, bicause we haue a more
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13276:29"/> diuine and Christian knowledge: we see, and allow of better things, (as Medea saith) but imbrace &amp; practise the woorst: we see the dangers and hazards, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer our heads, if we obey our lusts; but yet we follow them with great gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines; by meanes whereof, we run into infinite errors, and sticke not to heape sinne vpon sinne, that we may the more liberally enioy our pleasure, whereof we haue an example in Dauid. Dauid first <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> Sam. 11. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>, 3, 4.</note> saw, then lusted, next yeelded, after prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised, and so to most filthie adulterie, was added horrible murder, the cause of the <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>erse. 15.</note> Lords heauie displeasure against him. It had been well for him, if he had not seen, <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>erse 27.</note> and he had been happy, if he had not as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to his lusting eies: but heerein he was most miserable, in that he sought to fulfil, and satisfie his lust. So little begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ende with tragicall excutions: A sparke of fire neglected, maketh a cole, and a cole not extinguished, engendreth a great flame, which spareth no more the stately towers of princes, than the poore cottages of pesants. Lust is this sparke which lurketh in our bowels, if we yeeld neuer so little thereunto, it becommeth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13276:29"/> a cole, and if we adde any farther matter, it groweth to a flame, which wasteth and consumeth, first our bodies, and then yeeldeth (without repentance) both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and soule to the inquenchable flames of hel fire. A litle seed, or plant maketh a great tree; &amp; as out of one stocke spring many boughes, &amp; out of those boughs many branches, &amp; out of those branches many twigs, so as the tree becommeth tall, large, and spreadeth verie far: so out of one affection, not resisted, proceed manie vices, many horrible and grieuous sinnes. Thus couetousnes hath manie companions; extorsion, vsurie, oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, grinding the faces of the poore, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, with manie other attendants. Thus a little choler nourished, bringeth foorth wrath; wrath, hatred; hatred, murther; and murther, without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, desperation: heerof Cain is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. Thus lust engendreth liking; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, longing; longing, practise; at last adulterie is committed, and perhaps co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered also with murther, if murther may be couered: heerof Dauid is an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but Dauid found mercie, repented, and was saued. But the difference in this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13276:30"/> comparison may be this, that the twigs are lesse than the branches, &amp; the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches than the boughes; but the growth and increase of our affections is cleane contrarie: it serueth therefore especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this purpose, to shew vnto vs, that there is no sinne which goeth alone, and that one sinne nourished groweth migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, spreadeth far, and carieth vs as it were into a maine sea of desperate wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: and therefore as it standeth vs vpon, to withstand the beginnings: so to labor to cut downe this plant of sinne which groweth within vs, that it may not ouer-spread the soule. If thy gazing eies haue stirred vp thy gadding minde, rest there; consent not to thy filthie appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite: or if thou be so vnhappie, by the frailtie of thy flesh to yeeld cōsent, yet in any case forbear to practise, least hauing thus polluted the temple of the Lord, he depart from thee, and giue thee ouer to all vncleannes. If thou feele thy selfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with choler, leaue there; let not wrath ouertake thee: or if thou be so vnhappie, that it proceed thus far; yet let not the sunne go downe vpon thy wrath, least hatred mooue thee to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13276:30"/> vpon mischiefe in thy bed, and so thou be drawen to commit some bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die action.</p>
                     <p>This course is to be taken in the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of all other affections, which may be fitly compared (in my poore opinion) to a wild colt, for diuers considerations. First, as the one must be broken, so must the other in like sort be brideled, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise as the one will carie his rider head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, he careth not whither, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the steepines of mountaine, or depth of riuer, to the destruction of them both; so the other will violently carie vs into al mischiefe, without heed or regard of the manifold dangers, wherunto that violent course is subiect. Next, when by the industrie of the rider, and strength of the bridle, this colt shal be compelled somewhat better to knowe himselfe; it shall be meet to acquaint him often with the bridle, and not to pamper him in the stable, without any farther exercise: so it shal be expedient for vs, when we haue brought our affections to some measure of conformitie, not to rest there, and giue them a time of libertie; but to labor wholy to subdue them without intermis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13276:31"/> And as by this exercise and good managing of this colt, you shall easily at the last rule him with the bridle, terrifie him with the rod, and set him forward with the spur: so hauing once conquered these rebellious affectiōs, by such means as shall be presently declared, you shall afterward rule them without any great difficultie, and by discretion and good gouernment, bring them to a verie good temper. But still remember this, that a strong headed horse, that is, our vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie concupiscence, hath neede of strong rains: and to a slow jade, that is, to our backward &amp; dull nature in good things, the rod and spur shall be verie profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The combat of Hercules with the giant Anteus doth also represent vnto vs the nature of our fleshlie affections, and sheweth in what sort we are to deale with them. First, Anteus is strong; so are our affections: Hercules applieth all his strength to ouercome Anteus; so ought we to subdue our affections: Anteus will not forgo his hold, but cleaueth close to the earth from whence hee receiueth strength; so do our carnall affections, they cleaue fast vnto our earthlie bodies,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13276:31"/> where they are fostered and nourished: Hercules laboreth this one thing especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, to ouercome Anteus by lifting him vp from the earth; so must we labour to conquer our affections by mortifieng of them, and lifting vp our minds to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: Hercules after a long combat, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotten aduantage, crusheth Anteus in peeces, and spareth not his life; so must we striue in such sort to crucifie and tread our carnall affections vnder foote, that they may not be able to rise, and rebell any more against our soules.</p>
                     <p>We must deale with them as wise prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do with factious subiects, or as good surgeons do with rotten members; cut them off: otherwise, as one factious and seditious subiect seduceth manie; as one rotten and putrified member corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth manie: so one affection stirreth vp another, and gathering strength maketh such mutinies against the soule, as will not be repressed.</p>
                     <p>But how shall we auoid the first temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations? How shall we cut downe the spreading tree of our fleshlie affections? With what bridle may this colt be best tamed? With what weapons may An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13276:32"/> bee subdued and conquered? By these: the sword of the spirit, which is the word of the Lord; earnest and hartie praier; auoiding opportunitie of time and place; honest and lawfull matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; which are all so manie axes, to lop downe the branches of lust and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscence, so manie snaffles to hold in the head of this wild colt, &amp; so many strong weapons to withstand the assaults of the flesh, and such as are prescribed vnto vs in the word. Therefore, when we feele our selues touched with the flattering prouocation of our concupiscence, wee may not consult with the flesh, but wee must haue recourse to the Lord, &amp; craue his assistance by earnest praier, that it wil please him to mortifie olde Adam, and that these rebellious and obstinate passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be remoued. We must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our owne infirmitie and weaknes, and seeke for strength at his hands; we are not able to wrestle with Satan; we are not able to conquer our owne flesh: <hi>It is God that giueth both to will and to do,</hi> and <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> without his diuine assistance we can do nothing. When thy flesh therfore rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, oppose Gods spirit; it is a strong
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13276:32"/> buckler: when thy affections are muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and band themselues against thy soule; oppose the complet harnes which <note place="margin">Ephes. 6. 17</note> S. Paul deliuereth vnto thee. If Sathan tempt thee with fleshlie desires; saie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, it is written, <hi>Thou shalt not commit</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 18.</note>
                        <hi>adulterie.</hi> If thy flesh prouoke thee to yeeld to Sathans suggestions; make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that <hi>Thy bodie is the temple of the holie</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 19. verse 18.</note>
                        <hi>Ghost: That euerie other sinne is without the bodie,</hi> but this filthie and abhominable sinne is within thy bowels, and most horribly defileth Gods temple: Say that Christ is thy bridegroome, and hath <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 1.</note> giuen vp his bodie on the crosse, that he might preserue both thy bodie and soule to those euerlasting ioies, which he hath prepared for his elect. Thus learne out of the word, what thou oughtest to do in these assaults, and praie withall that thou maist put these wholsome instructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in execution. God hath promised to heare and to grant those petitions, which tend to his honor, and which we aske in faith: <hi>He will not the death of a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ezec. 18. 32</note>
                        <hi>but that he should be conuerted vnto him, and liue.</hi> If our earthlie fathers grant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Luke. 11. 11</note> vs good things for the benefit of our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13276:33"/> bodies, when we aske them: how much more will our heauenlie father performe our godlie requests, which are referred to our soules health? And as our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fathers are sorie to see their sonnes by the loosenes of their conuersation, fall into anie extremitie: so no doubt is the spirit of God grieued, to see the worke of his hands, which he hath made and <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>sa. 119. 73 Gen. 1. 26. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>7.</note> fashioned in all perfection after his owne image, to fall awaie from him; and of his tender mercie and compassion calleth him home, and restoreth him againe to his fauor: So he called Dauid, when by true repentance hee acknowledged his <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Sam. 12. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>3.</note> hainous offences, and wiped awaie the deepe staines which his vglie sinnes, first of adulterie, and then of murther, had made in his soule. And these are the principall weapons where with our flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie lusts are subdued.</p>
                     <p>Some others there are, which are not a litle also auaileable to preserue vs from the snares of <hi>Dalila;</hi> namely the auoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of oportunitie of time and place. Lust is increased by looking, &amp; lust with looking, engender good liking: Dauid looked from the roofe of his pallace, <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Sam. 11. 2</note>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13276:33"/> and lusted, and liking, rested not vntil he had satisfied his lust. Auoid likewise the <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 33.</note> companie and conference with <hi>Dalila,</hi> for bad communication corrupteth good maners, and bad companie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs also bad companions. He that <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 27.</note> taketh fire in his bosome, must needes sindge his clothes: he that goeth vppon <note place="margin">Verse. 28.</note> coles, cannot choose but burne his feete: it is hard to touch pitch, and not to be defiled: one scald sheepe, corrupteth a whole flocke, and to be but neere to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie contagious place, is verie dangerous. What greater contagiō than that, which not onely infecteth the bodie with mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous diseases; but also ladeth the soule with greeuous sins, and maketh both to become so vglie, as man sometimes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know the one, and the Lord refuseth to acknowledge the other? The conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of these things are forcible in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery well disposed mind: and me thinks, though the wicked will not auoide the companie of <hi>Dalila</hi> for the Lords sake, nor for their soules sake: yet they should haue some regard at the least to their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and be deterred from this bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation, in respect of the grieuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13276:34"/> wherunto they are oftetimes sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect by accōpanieng with <hi>Dalila.</hi> This also were a profitable meditation, for such as feele their corrupt nature to delight in such company: what is <hi>Dalila?</hi> What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit shall I get by hir? What are they that resort vnto hir? What hath hapned vnto others by hir? To what purpose go I vnto hir? What is it that prouoketh me to visit hir? <hi>Dalila</hi> is a vicious &amp; bad woman: No profit is to be expected, but rather cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain losse from <hi>Dalila:</hi> she is a companion for all commers, &amp; those the scum of the earth, Ruffians, Roysters, and such like infamous persons: this man was weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie before he fell acquainted with hir; now a begget: that man had his health before he frequented hir companie; now woorse than a creeple: lust entiseth me to visite hir, no true loue or deuotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hir, it is nothing else that carrieth me so far from common reason and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but the satisfaction of my fleshly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires. These fewe things well weighed, woulde easily make vs to abhor and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test the companie of <hi>Dalila,</hi> and to saie with Demosthenes: <hi>Non emam tanti poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere:</hi> I will not buie repentance so deer.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13276:34"/> Idlenes must also be auoided by him, that will suppresse his fleshlie lusts: <hi>Res age, tutus eris,</hi> saith the Poet; Be doing somewhat, and thou shalt be safe. If <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> had followed the course which he had once embraced to subdue and conquere the enimies of the Lord: <hi>Dalila</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer subdued nor conquered <hi>Samson:</hi> if Dauid had not gazed idlie from the <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> roofe of his pallace, it had not entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dauids hart, to defile Bersabe: while Hercules busied himselfe to cut off Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras heads, Hercules had no minde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any minions: but when he gaue ouer to performe like actions of honor &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; he fell into wretched Omphales lap, and became a slaue to hir, and his owne affections. If he had considered with what difficultie the growing heads of Hydra were cut off, and how they still increased, vntill he had dispatcht them al at once; he would haue made that profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table application, which some others since haue done, that it is in vaine to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer one affection, vnlesse we tame and bridle them all.</p>
                     <p>Nowe I cannot subscribe to our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists doctrine, that forbid marriage vnto
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13276:35"/> some men, which is a present remedy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all, to auoide the snares of <hi>Dalila;</hi> a doctrine flat contrarie vnto the instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lord in Genesis the second and <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>en. 2. 18. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>en. 8. 17. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>eb. 13. 4. Cor. 7. 2.</note> eight Chapter: as also against the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Christ and his Apostles in manie places. But it is no strange matter, that they are enimies to marriage, who are so good friends vnto <hi>Dalila,</hi> and haue hir at their commandement. He that wil but looke into Stephanus french Apologie for Herodotus, shall finde such stuffe confirmed by credible circumstances; as he will easily be induced to detest this papisticall position. And who can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that butcherlie execution, of so many thousands of poore infants, whose heads were founde in pope Gregories ponde; and not abhor those lecherous shauelings and this their doctrine? And if in Gregories ponde were found so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thousands: how many millions may we thinke might haue beene founde at that time, before, and since, in other like places of the world, where these fat and idle caterpillers are woont to reside neer about their minions? Mariage I saie is lawful in all, bicause God hath ordained
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13276:35"/> it; and mariage is also necessarie in all estates and conditions, for aswell the mightie prince, as the poore pesant, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the lay man, as the spirituall person, carieth in his bosome that fire, which will not be extinguished, without this water, vnlesse by some speciall gift from aboue, which is a verie rare matter. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid a mightie king, was subiect vnto it; Salomon his sonne, was too much addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto it; the one a man after Gods owne hart; the other, the wisest prince that euer ruled. And Paul a painefull mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the Gospel, and one of the most faithfull stewards of the word, that hath beene from the beginning, saith: that <hi>He felt another law in his members, rebelling</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 23 24.</note>
                        <hi>against the law of his minde, which led him captiue vnto the law of sinne:</hi> And so vpon this consideration, he breaketh out in this exclamation: <hi>O wretched man, who shall deliuer me from the bodie of this death?</hi> But if any man hath this gift of chastitie, which the presumptuous Antichristian prelats chalenge vnto themselues, it is in my opinion the labouring man, who by his bodily exercise, cooleth the heate of lust, and by continuall paines about
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13276:36"/> his affaires, giueth not place to lasciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts: but auoiding idlenes, is free from those wanton cogitations, which stir vp lust, and kindle the cole of concupiscence, which euerie man bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth about him: But those idle abbey-lubbers of all other conditions, seeme to haue the least portion of this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie gift, bieause they cease not to pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per their flesh with all delicacies, liue at ease, and attende onely their pleasure, which are the greatest enimies to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie that may be. But if neither the godliest, as Dauid, nor the wisest, as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, nor the strongest as <hi>Samson,</hi> could auoid the snare of lust: let this libertie, at the least, be freely granted to all; to imbrace the meanes which the Lorde hath appointed for the tempering of their heate, and let euerie man that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth this kinde of rebellion in his flesh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst gods spirit, choose vnto him, not a <hi>Dalila,</hi> but an honest wife, ioined vnto him in lawfull matrimonie, and so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue his vessell pure and vndefiled, that the holy Ghost may delight to dwell and abide therein; in which choise, that man shall haue attained to the highest degree
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13276:36"/> of worldly happines, whose good hap is, to finde a wife of good quality, of honest parentage, of chaste conuersation, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious disposition, a Sara, a Rachell, a Rebecca, an Esther, a Iudith; in a worde, a vertuous woman, who for hir price (as <note place="margin">Pro. 31. 10</note> Salomon affirmeth) is far aboue pearles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The seale of secrets.</head>
                     <p>THus haue we set downe the best <hi>Recipe,</hi> for this dangerous disease of lust, and concupiscence, which the most learned spirituall phisitions haue obserued, to be most profitable for him that hath a care of his souls health. And now hauing performed this taske, according to my first purpose, and rude skill; it is time to looke more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie into <hi>Samsons</hi> frailtie and infirmitie, in discouering a secret of this moment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Dalila.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The text saith, that <hi>Bicause she was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate continually, and vexed his soule: therefore he told hir all his hart.</hi> Wherein appeereth, that <hi>Samson</hi> had some feeling, and consideration of that which might ensue, by reuealing of this secret; else why shoulde his soule haue beene thus vexed? But it seemeth that his fleshlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13276:37"/> flattered him too much, and gaue him hope, that <hi>Dalila</hi> woulde be trustie and faithful to conceale the same, whereupon he might be induced to make triall of hir fidelitie, and secrecie: Like vnto the theefe, who hoping that his theft shall not be discouered; is content when he seeth any fit oportunity, to take a purse, or some other good booty, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may enrich him selfe: which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration causeth him to forget the danger which the law inflicteth vpon such malefactors: for if this conceit could be throughly setled in his mind, that there is no wickednes done in secret but shall be reuealed, and that the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes <note place="margin">Luk. 8. 17.</note> is their due, that enter into these vniust actions, to enrich them selues by the spoile; it would no doubt strike a terror and feare in him, to violate the lawes of God and man. And yet such is the wilfull blindnes which is in manie; such is the hardnes of their hart, (in which number let <hi>Samson</hi> haue his place) as seeing, they will not see the dangers, whereinto they voluntarilie cast them selues by their desperate actions; which proceedeth of no other cause, then that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13276:37"/> resisting Gods spirit, they giue the raines to that wilde colt of their affections, which will not harken to any reason, or holsome admonition, tending to their better securitie and safety.</p>
                     <p>But bicause <hi>Dalila vexeth Samsons soule euen to the death; therefore he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hir all his hart:</hi> which words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine many good lessons, how we are to behaue our selues in matter of secrecie, concerning either our owne states, or the state of others. First <hi>Samson</hi> vttered not this secret, but with great importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, euen in the vexation and anguish of his soule; whereby we see the rashnes and lightnes of those condemned, that vtter all kindes of secrets euen with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, they care not to whom, without respect of the danger which may ensue. Their harts would breake, if they should not reueale the greatest matter that hath beene communicated vnto them, yea they wil voluntarily prouoke others, and giue some signification vnto them, that they haue intelligence of some se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, to the ende they may be prouoked, or intreated to disclose the same; and then will they neuerthelesse binde you
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13276:38"/> with conditions, that you shall not disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it to any other, howsoeuer liberallie they themselues deale therein, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish it to all commers. By which meane, whether it be a matter of state concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the common wealth, or any other matter, the publication whereof carieth danger; they hinder the course of those proceedings, which otherwise might haue had good successe, and procure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themselues the note of trustles bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. Some others there are, troubled with like humour, yet not so liberall in the reuealing of matters of moment, but will aduenture onely to trust some deere friend, of whose fidelitie they haue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hope, then experience; and so they speede accordingly, for this friend hath also one whom he imbraceth with like affection: and the third, maketh account also of his friend, and so the secret is tos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from friend to friend, that it flieth very shortly into all parts. Thus <hi>Samson</hi> trusted <hi>Dalila</hi> as his good friend, but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lila</hi> esteeming better of the Philistines, than of <hi>Samson,</hi> and ioining with them in their malicious practises; made him to paie deerely for reposing of that trust in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13276:38"/> hir. To be secret in deed, in all causes of importance, is not found in all; although it be the part of euerie honest man, in all honest causes committed vnto them, to be secret. But bicause this fault of impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting secrets to friends, is common, and incident to manie, and that so manie dangers haue growen aswell in generall to the states of kings, and their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; as in particular to seuerall persons: it shall not be amisse to consider some circumstances, to be obserued in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe; which I will endeuour to set down the more briefely, bicause this discourse is alreadie become more tedious then was at the first intended: and yet I hope the well disposed will gather some profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table notes, not altogither vnwoorthy their reading. The principall circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or heads offered to our considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are these three; what secrets are to be concealed; by whom; and from whom. The secrets to be concealed, are such as concerne the estate of thy prince, thy countrey, thy friend, thy selfe. The two first so depende ech of other, as he that reuealeth any matter to the preiudice of the one, must of necessity hurt the other;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13276:39"/> bicause the prince being the principall stay and piller of the countrey; it must needs go ill therewith, if his person be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waie endangered: and if the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey sustaine any detriment by inuasion, sedition, treason, practise, or any other like accident; the prince hath a share in the calamities which by these meanes shall arise. Now the securitie of princes, and their kingdomes, stande verie much vpon the keeping secret of their consul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and resolutions in any weightie causes, concerning their negociations with other princes: their deliberations and purposes for the atchieuing of any honorable enterprise, tending to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement of gods glorie, the cause of religion, the repose of their countrey, the recouerie of their right detained by the vsurper, the preuention of danger for their better securitie, pollitike stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagemes for the discouerie of treasons, and other practises of the ill affected: these and such like, are matters which occur to be discust, &amp; handled in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret counsell of princes; the reuealing whereof may ouerthrow all their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, and draw therewith many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13276:39"/> euents.</p>
                     <p>There are also secrets, which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt friend and friend, as likewise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt others of other state and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which are not of the qualitie of the former; and yet vnmeet to be reuealed. Manie secret contracts and bargaines; manie priuate conferences of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesticall causes, the present publishing whereof would be occasion of losse to the parties; although the danger of these inconueniences being past, they would be content to discouer the cause of their former secrecie. There are diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther secrets of greater moment betwixt friends, which somtimes concerne their liues, somtimes their honor and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, sometimes their goodes and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, which may be conserued by si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, wherein there is an honest dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, not repugnant to the worde of God, if those secrets tend not to his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor, the hurt of our prince, countrie, or neighbor: for these are the bounds and limits of secrecie.</p>
                     <p>There are also some secrets which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne euerie mans particular, and which pertaine onelie to himselfe, and such as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13276:40"/> he shal do himselfe wrong, if he trust any other with them: which kind of secrets somtimes occur in the course of our life, and touch also the state and hazard of our life; and this one example of <hi>Samson</hi> may be sufficient to admonish vs to deal warily therein. He that cannot be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to himselfe, how can he be faithfull to another; or how can he hope another should be faithfull to him? Canst thou expect more at another mans hands, thā thou wilt performe towards thy selfe? But if it be thy good hap to find such a friend, thinke that he loueth thee better than thou louest thy selfe: but if any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger happen vnto thee by thy babling, impute it not so much to thy friend, as to thy owne follie and indiscretion. If <hi>Samson</hi> had loued himselfe, he woulde neuer haue vttered a secret of such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence to <hi>Dalila,</hi> and trusted hir better therewith (who of all friends is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfullest) than his owne hart: which rashnes and credulitie in him, brought foorth tragicall effects, and <hi>Samsons</hi> bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 19. 21. 30.</note> cost him his haire, which was his strength; his eies, which were the guide of his bodie; and he became at the last
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13276:40"/> his owne executioner, that he might be auenged on his enimies.</p>
                     <p>Now let vs consider by whom secrets are to be concealed. As princes haue manie secret causes, concerning the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruation of their state, which I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie briefly touched: so it is of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie that they haue graue and wise coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellers, to assist them in the execution of such as are of greatest consequence; as also to aduise them to such good course, as shall be most expedient and profitable for the other affaires of their gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but godlie pollicie and faithfull secrecie must be ioined togither: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise their consultations and resolutions will haue verie vnhappie issue. For if in a whole bodie of Councell or state there be but one, whose hart is in his mouth, the determinations &amp; conclusions, how secretly soeuer concealed by the rest, will be published by him, to the great preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice &amp; dammage of the whole countrie: for a man void of secrecie, is like a vessell full of chinks, put in what liquor you will, let it be neuer so costlie, it will run out. But as a good husband will first trie his vessell with water, before he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13276:41"/> to powre wine therein: so it shal be expedient, that some good experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be had of the fidelitie and secrecie of those that are called to this high place of honor, on whose shoulders lieth a good part of the burden of the common wealth, and into whose harts are pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and shut vp the secrets of princes, and of their state. We locke vp our rich iewels and treasure, not onelie in strong towers, but we haue there also iron cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to receiue them, that the theefe may not easily obtaine his bootie: so ought the mouthes of Counsellers, to whom the iewels and treasure; that is, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of their prince and countrie are committed, to be not onelie as strong towers to containe the same, but also their harts must be as iron coffers, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in these secret iewels may be carefully and safely preserued. And in this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, this may be in briefe the resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance: the lips are in steed of the wals; the teeth, the doore; the toong, the kay; the hart, the coffer; the iewels, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets.</p>
                     <p>This lesson may also serue for Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadors residing in forren parts, to learne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13276:41"/> what they can of the state of those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and of the proceedings of those princes with whom they negociate; but to be faithfull and secret in the causes which concerne the state of their owne countrie: wherein if they shall at any time be lauish, they are to be held in no better place, than in the ranke and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of traitors.</p>
                     <p>Secretaries also to noble men, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther seruants to whom the waightie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of their masters are committed, must learne to be silent and secret in all matters, so far as their duties towards God and their prince will permit. It ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth likewise to all other degrees and callings whatsoeuer: to captains, to sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to all magistrates and officers of cities and townes, to publike persons, to priuate persons, to all persons; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them it reacheth particularly to those that professe the name of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and vnder that name do insinuate themselues into mens harts, with whom the sincere and plaine meaning friend dealeth very liberally, and imparteth his secrets of what nature soeuer. But as it falleth out, that he who pretendeth the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13276:42"/> name of a Damon, doth oftentimes play the Daemon, the dissembling and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les hypocrite: so haue we instructions thereby, as well to haue great regard in the choise of our friends, as also discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in cōmunicating secrets vnto them. A perfect friend is not inquisitiue to know more, than thou shalt be willing of thine owne accord to impart vnto him: and if thou finde such an importunate friend, as desireth to be acquainted with more than thou thinkest to be meete for him, such a one as is alwaies asking, and seeketh to enter into thy hart; thou hast iust cause to suspect him, &amp; to craue lesse of his acquaintance, according to that admonition of the Poet:</p>
                     <q>Percunctatorem fugito, nam garrulus idem est.</q>
                     <q>
                        <l>Flie far from him that questions oft doth moue,</l>
                        <l>He is a blab, and such thou shalt him proue.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>And such a friend was <hi>Dalila.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are manie notable examples extant, by the which is expressed more liuelie vnto vs, how well secrecie becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all degrees. We read of Alexander, that hauing receiued letters from his mother, containing matter of some good importance, when hee had perused the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13276:42"/> same, he communicated the secret also to his friend Ephestion: but taking his signet from his finger, he sealed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Ephestions lips; shewing thereby what he expected at his hands: and we finde not that Ephestion at anie time plaied the blab. It is also recorded of Cato, that being demanded the cause of his stinking breath; answered, that manie secrets had beene kept so close in his stomack, that they were become rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which was the reason that his breth was so vnsauorie. These two great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages, the one the friend and counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of a prince; the other (if my memorie faile me not) a graue senator of Rome, may be examples to those of like place and calling, to shew how well faithfull se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie is agreeable with their estates. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celius Metellus being asked by one of the Tribunes, of his resolution concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning some weightie martiall cause, made answer, that if he thought his shirt were acquainted with the secret, he would cast it into the fire. A lesson to be imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of all Generals, Captains, and other officers that haue charge. The seruāts of Plancius could not be forced by any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:13276:43"/> to reueale vnto the enimies of their master who sought his death, where Plancius had hidden himselfe, to saue his life: A lesson to be learned of good ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, to carie themselues faithfull and secret towards their masters in like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</p>
                     <p>The last consideration is, from whom secrets are to be concealed. The generall note may be this, that weightie secrets are not to be imparted to anie, whom they nothing concerne. Secrets of state whereof dependeth the securitie of the prince and countrie, may not be disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to forren princes, who will make their profit of all aduertisements; not to such as haue addicted themselues to their seruice; not to strangers; not to es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pials and intelligencers; not to the ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in religion the treacherous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist, who like the viper is content to rent the bowels of his best nurse, euen for the inbred malice which he beareth towards those that are not of his humor and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position: and that such are not to be trusted with secrets, their practises in all times, but especially in this latter age do sufficiently teach vs. I neede not looke
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13276:43"/> backe to manie yeeres; the woorthie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of so manie within few moneths for horrible conspiracies against their prince and countrie, doth testifie thus much vnto vs, who not onelie reuealed the secrets of this state vnto the forren enimie, the affection of the rotten mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the same, their deuotion to ioine with the aduersarie, the weaknes of the land, the meanes to performe their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous intended enterprises: but also were come to the point of the execution of these most bloodie desseins, if God had not put a bridle into their mouthes, and staied the violent course which they held in their butcherly proceedings.</p>
                     <p>Neither must <hi>Dalila</hi> be made priuie vnto <hi>Samsons</hi> secrets; that is, bad women must not be made partakers of those things, the discouery wherof may be dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous vnto <hi>Samsons</hi> life. For <hi>Dalila</hi> being of an inconstant affection, will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the impression of any secret; and being also of a light toong, will deceiue thee, and reueale the same. Now a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion might be made in generall; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther secrets may be safely committed to that sexe, and particularly to our wiues:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13276:44"/> wherein although there be diuers exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which induce some to be of opiniō, that it is not meete to impart anie secret whatsoeuer to any womā; which their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniō seemeth to be grounded especially vpon the double experience which <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> had; first of his wife, who reuealed his riddle: next of <hi>Dalila,</hi> who bereaued him of his haire: as also vpon Fuluius wiues indiscreet vttering of that which he had communicated vnto hir, concerning Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus intention for his successor in the empire: as likewise vpon Papirius Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textatus mothers importunity to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the secrets of the Senate: a matter so wisely handled by Papirius, being but a childe, as it remaineth in record to his perpetuall commendation: yet do I not subscribe to the opinion of these men; but do thinke that all houshould and priuate secrets, not concerning any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cause of state, may be safely commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to discreet, and godly disposed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, such as are described vnto vs in the last of Salomons Prouerbs. But there is a discretion also to be vsed heerein, we must be sure to know them to be such; and we must haue some experience of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13276:44"/> their fidelitie, which lesson I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deliuered to be obserued likewise in men. Thus one of the Catos is saide to haue trusted his wife with a pretended secret, which caried a shewe of good im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, yea such as being indeed true, might haue cost him his life: but Catos wife, although perhaps honester than <hi>Dalila,</hi> yet as vntrusty as <hi>Dalila,</hi> reuealed the same; whereby Cato made a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble experience of his wiues tatling dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, and of that common prouerbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs: Trie before thou trust. This is an infirmitie incident to the greater part of this sexe, but godly and vertuous women are able by a better considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their duties, in these cases, to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per their toongs, and to bridle their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections which mooue them to reueale secrets.</p>
                     <p>It is time to make an end, I haue been ouerlong in this discourse, and <hi>Dalila</hi> (I know) will cun me no thanke, for my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousnes. I hope that the wiser, discreet, and temperate matrones, into whose hands the same shal fall, will giue the best construction vnto my poore labor, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my purpose hath not been to exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13276:45"/> or mooue them in any sort; but by discouering the ouglie portreature of <hi>Dalila,</hi> and shewing the frailtie of <hi>Samson, Dalila</hi> may learne to amend hir maners, and cease to practise to corrupt <hi>Samson;</hi> and <hi>Samson</hi> looking into his infirmitie, may endeuour to auoid the suttletie and snares of <hi>Dalila:</hi> Which God grant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:45"/>
                  <p> A GODLIE MEDITATION vpon the 41. 42. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the 10. Chapter of <hi>S. Lukes Gospell,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining especially THE <hi>Profit of reproofe, togither with</hi> the necessitie and <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the word</hi> of God.</p>
                  <p>LONDINI, Impensis G. Bishop.</p>
                  <p>1588</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:46"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:13276:46"/>
                  <head>A godly meditation vpon the 41. and 42. verses of the 10. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>of Saint</hi> LVKES Gospell.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Luk. ch. 10. verse. 41. 42</bibl>
                        <p>Iesus answered and said vnto hir; Martha, Martha, thou carest and art troubled about manie things:</p>
                        <p>But one thing is needfull, Marie hath chosen the good part, which shall not be taken away from hir.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE verses con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine an answer of our Sauior Christ, to the expostulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of busie <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> against hir reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious sister <hi>Marie:</hi> wherin may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued these two speciall things: first, a reproofe of <hi>Marthas</hi> ouer-great careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes about hir houshold affaires; next, an allowance or commendation of <hi>Maries</hi> choise to heare Christ, carefully occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about his fathers busines. And heere manie good lessons occur to be learned
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13276:47"/> of ech part, wherein I purpose not to be ouer-curious: onelie I will gather such principall notes, with profitable applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the text it selfe yeeldeth to the sense and capacitie of euerie good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, that studiously delighteth to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon the law of the Lord: and to auoide confusion and disorder in the handling of these verses, with the notes which are offered to our consideration; I will briefly discourse of ech particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as the words of the Scripture shall lead vs.</p>
                  <p>And first, in generall occurreth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of our Sauior Christ against <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha:</hi> wherein I obserue, as may be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the 11. of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Gospell, that these two sisters, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 33.</note> were such, of whom he made singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar account and estimation, such as were highlie in his fauor, and caried no small reputation with him, which he testified by that great, woonderfull, and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie miracle, in raising <hi>Lazarus</hi> from <note place="margin">verse. 44.</note> the dead, and in weeping and lamenting for his decease. A thing seldom obserued in him, howsoeuer his humane nature made him subiect to like affections, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13276:47"/> with all due moderation; which giueth vs this good instruction, that how neare or deere soeuer our friends are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: yet that we ought not to spare them, but with all discretion meete and conuenient, to admonish them of their faults, and to reprooue them according to the qualitie of their errors. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther must not winke at the sonne, nor the sonne at the father; the mother must not soothe the daughter, nor the daughter the mother; the master must not flatter his scholler, nor the scholler his master: in a word, there is no regard to be had of affinitie, no respect of friendship, no feare of authoritie, no doubt of danger, when flesh and blood forgetting it selfe, or rather forgetting the Lord, is caried awaie with worldly respects from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie meditations, and from the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of diuine exercises. And heereunto we are bound as well in regard of the parties whose facts craue reformation, as also in respect of our selues; charitie, conscience, duty, and religion comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the one and the other. For if to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our neighbors ox or asse to go astray <note place="margin">Deut. 22. 1.</note> or perish, be forbiddē vs by the scripture:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13276:48"/> much more are we inioined to haue a christian care of their own soules health, that they wander not to the pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Euery man is subiect by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of his flesh, to seueral imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and errors, the pleasantnes whereof wil not permit him to looke so narrowly into himselfe, and to withdraw his feete from the euil waies wherin he hath been accustomed to walke. But as it is the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men to see better other mens faults, than their owne; and euen the best disposed haue their blemishes: so it standeth with the rule of Christianitie, and charitie, that hauing our eies thus opened, we should also haue a fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our brothers sinnes, and labor to reduce him into the right way of true religion, and godlines. We account him a perfect friend, and haue him in singular estimation, that forewarneth vs of anie temporall danger, and we see this often put in practise among vs; but in spiritual causes of far greater consequence, fewe or none giue admonition. We are good counsellers for the bodie, but carelesse for the soule; we are politike in those things which concerne our temporall
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13276:48"/> proceedings; but starke idiots in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of far higher qualitie; we haue our mouths open so long as no danger is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, but we will not accept of anie hard conditions, of losse, or displeasure; we haue shifts, and answers readie at all assaies, to excuse our remisse and colde dealing in gods cause. We can confesse and say that some men do not wel to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent themselues from the word, to prefer their worldly causes, before heauenlie exercises: but this man is my brother; I may not offende him; that man is my neighbour, I will not displease him; this man is my acquaintance, I may not breake with him; that man is a stranger, I haue nothing to do with him; this man is a magistrate, I stande in awe of him; that man is my friend, I am beholding to him, I am in his debt, I looke for some curtesie at his hands, he will take it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly to be reprooued, I shal be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted sawcie, and more bould than becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth me, to seeke his reformation. We are more bound now a daies to our eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies than to our friends: our enimies though reprochfully, discouer vnto vs our faults; our friendes partially shut
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13276:49"/> their eies, and will not behold them; our enimies, though maliciously, reprooue our vicious actions, our friends vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie suffer vs to wallow in our sinnes, and neuer labour to draw vs out of that vncleane sinke and puddle of iniquitie, and all forsooth, bicause they will not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs. This is not to follow the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Christ, whose estate in this world, by the testimonie of his owne mouth, was so poore, and subiect to so many ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities, as not hauing any place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to rest his head, it might haue beene a <note place="margin">Matt. 8. 20.</note> sufficient matter to mooue him to stop his mouth, in a cause which tended to his owne benefit, and may seeme to haue proceeded from the tender affection which <hi>Martha</hi> bare vnto him: but Christ preferred the care of hir soule, before the curiousnes of his owne intertainement, and without respect, was bold to tell hir roundly of hir fault. Thus did <hi>Moyses</hi> to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and yet he was his brother; thus <note place="margin">Exo. 32. 21.</note> did <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> to <hi>Herode,</hi> and yet he was <note place="margin">Matt. 14. 4. Mark. 6. 18.</note> a man of blood; thus did <note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 24. 10.</note>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12. 9</note>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 2. 10.</note>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Saul,</hi> and yet he was a frantike tyrant; thus did <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and yet he was a mightie king; thus did Iob to his wife,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13276:49"/> and yet she was his owne flesh; thus did <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 23. &amp; 26. 40. Acts. 3. 12.</note> Christ to <hi>Peter,</hi> and yet he was one of his beloued disciples; thus did <hi>Peter</hi> to the stiffenecked Iewes, and yet he was dailie exposed to most miserable dangers; thus did <hi>Ionas</hi> to the Niniuites, and yet he was <note place="margin">Ionas. 3. 4.</note> in the midst of an insolent and crooked generation.</p>
                  <p>I finde in a prophane writer this sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; <hi>Amici vitia qui fert, facit sua:</hi> He that beareth with his friendes faultes, doth make them his own. A sentence, in sense sauoring of great religion, and woorthie to be imbraced of those that haue some better taste of Christ, and that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to auoide the waight of so heauie a burthen.</p>
                  <p>This condemneth all flatterers, who are so far from disliking, or reproouing of their friends errors, (if flatterers may be termed friends) that they make <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> beleeue he is a God with <hi>Nicesias;</hi> that <hi>Herods</hi> voice is the voice of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, <note place="margin">Act. 12. 22</note> with those peruerse clawbacks; and like the foxe in <hi>Aesops</hi> fables, that the Crowe is a faire birde, that his notes are pleasant, and make a most sweet consort: yea they will laugh with that flattering
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13276:50"/> parasite bicause <hi>Dionysius</hi> laugheth, and yet cannot yeeld any reason of their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous gestures: A most dangerous, and pernicious generation, and not to be auoided without great circumspecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and iudgement: for flesh and bloode being tickled with praise, and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with reprehension, is more addicted to that which bringeth but a momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane sweete, than to that which yeeldeth the least sower in the world.</p>
                  <p>And here we may consider, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men we ought to be in our repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions, and what circumstances are conuenient to be obserued in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. As we must be zealous, so ought we also to be discreet; as we must not be partiall, so ought we to be prudent; as we must not be curious, so ought we not to be too currish; as we must not be blind, so ought we not to be too sharp sighted; as we must not be remisse, so ought we not to be too rigorous; as we must not lay cusshens vnder mens elbowes, so ought we not to set daggers to their harts; but ech of these extremes, are to be tempered with all Christian modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Zeale must be guided with discreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13276:50"/> otherwise it will violently carry vs far beyond the bounds prescribed thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and if there are bounds and limites prescribed vnto our zeale euen in Gods causes: how much more ought other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and our toongs to be modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that we ouerlash not, nor come to short in our duties. He that is partiall, will not discerne, but he that is prudent, can, and will iudge, and censure mens doings; he that is curious, obserueth more than enough; &amp; he that is currish, barketh with opē mouth at euery thing; he that is blind, sleepeth in his owne er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; and being without sense, will not behold the ouglines of others sinnes; and he that is too sharp sighted stareth so long vpon them, that he forgetteth him selfe, and peering into mens actions more narrowly than there is cause, incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the note of a busie body, which he iustly deserueth; he that is too remisse, is carelesse of his brothers soules health, and he that is too rigorous, doth often vexe his soule, and sometimes by indis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet admonitiōs driueth him to despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. We must not barke like dogs, nor bite like woolues at al that we see or
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13276:51"/> heare in our brethren. Howbeit I do not disallow seuere reprehensions in some cases, so the same be accompanied with some due circumstances. In sum, these few things seeme meete to be obserued: the party reprehending; the partie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended; the maner of the reproofe; the qualitie of the offence; the place where, and the time when. Euerie man ought to reprehende, but euery man ought not to reprehende all; euerie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is to be reprehended, but euery of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence deserueth not like reprehension▪ Reprehend; but reprehend in fit place, and reprehend in due time. These rules dulie obserued, we shall shew therein no <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 8. Pro. 10. 12.</note> lesse Christian charitie, which couereth the multitude of sinnes; than charitable discretion, which maketh our reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to be wel taken, &amp; bringeth foorth due reformation. Desperate diseases, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire desperate remedies, and desperate wickednes craueth sharpe rebuke. Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like offences are slanderous, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to receiue either publike admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or correction. Better the corroziue which healeth with paine, thē the stinge of the scorpion which killeth with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:13276:51"/> But as neere as we can, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hope to reclaime our brother, and if we see him not giuen ouer to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate sense, or wilfully obstinate without recouerie; let vs do our best endeuours, by priuate instructions, admonitions, and reprehensions, in as sharpe or milde termes as the fact requireth, to bring home the straieng sheepe.</p>
                  <p>Now what maner of men they ought to be that reprehend, may appeere in the person of our Sauior Christ; namelie of a spotles and vpright conuersation, of a cleane and incorrupt life, and especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voide of those imperfections which they note in others; otherwise as their admonitions, and instructions will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine verie small credite, so will they worke as little effect where so iust excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be taken against them. It is an old verse and verie true:</p>
                  <q>Turpe est doctori cum culpa redarguit ipsum.</q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Who blameth others, void must be of blame,</l>
                     <l>For like offence, yeelds like disgrace and shame.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>So as if we feele our selues free from the like absurdities, we may the more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reprooue others, as otherwise we shall neuer be able to sounde the bottome of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13276:52"/> their faults, bicause we shall finde a flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering humour within vs, which will mooue vs to sooth our selues, or rather our owne guiltie consciences will cause vs to stop our mouths.</p>
                  <p>Let vs proceed to the maner of Christs reprehension. He saith not simply, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> thou carest, and art troubled; but <hi>Martha, Martha, thou carest and art trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about many things.</hi> Which repetition seemeth to carie therewith great force, and argueth the greatnes of <hi>Marthas</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. It was no time for him to soothe hir, when he saw hir entred into so dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a course, and therefore to make hir to remember hir selfe, and to haue a more serious consideration of hir negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; he awaketh hir throughly with this double repetition, <hi>Martha, Martha:</hi> for otherwise it may be doubted shee would haue thought too well of hir acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, bicause they were referred to the benefit of Christ himselfe, and so haply in hir conceit deserued rather commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. But he giueth another maner of construction therunto by his sharpe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition: and although it may seeme to some, that he dealt verie hardly with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13276:52"/> hir, as well for the former respect, as in consideration that perhaps it was the first fault in this kind: yet may we learne heerby, as well by what rule we ought to measure our actions of curtesie and hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalitie; as also how sinne is to be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe in the blossom, and to be cut off betimes, before it grow to a head. For if Christ had winked at <hi>Marthas</hi> first negligence (if it were the first) it might haue been an occasion vnto hir to haue flattered hir self, and to haue made light estimation of that fault; and so thereby to take farther libertie to commit the like offence at some other time. Besides, the example (as all such examples are quickly imbraced and allowed of flesh and blood) might haue been dangerous to the rest of that familie, and serued them in steed of a warrant to make no difference of times and seasons, when there is question of anie temporal bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or other action tending thereunto. And this may be in part a reason why the words of Christ carie so sharpe a taste with them: whereunto may be added, that <hi>Martha</hi> seemed to haue forgotten hir selfe greatly, when as not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13276:53"/> to prefer hir housholde causes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heauenlie busines, would also haue drawen hir sister <hi>Marie</hi> into the like er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and hindered hir from hearing the comfortable tidings of the Gospell: Whereby we see all those condemned, who carieng small deuotion to the word themselues, do labor to peruert others; and from sermons do draw them to vain and idle exercises, or to some worldlie and temporall busines, without regard of the account which is to be made in that great day of the bestowing of their time. But I will not note <hi>Martha</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie wilfull intention to seduce hir sister <hi>Marie,</hi> as our idle, cold, and careles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors may iustly be noted: onelie it may be thought that this inconuenience would easily haue insued, if Christ had not vsed timely preuention. No doubt hir chiefe intent heerin was to haue the helpe of hir sister in those preparations, for the intertainment of our Sauiour, which haply she esteemed a sufficient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse of hir slacknes, or rather accounted it no slacknes at all: but this affection receiued a checke, and these great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations were the lesse regarded, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13276:53"/> so little regard was had of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore let our great feast-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers that are so curious in their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, so precise in their diet, learn, that there ought to be a Christian tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and moderation in their ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets; that they are not to exceede the measure of sobrietie prescribed; that fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galitie is to be preferred before super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie, and honest curtesie before nice curiositie; that Christ &amp; his poore mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are not to be excluded, who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 13.</note> to feede them with spirituall foode; and that they so intertaine them, as they may finde by their intertainment that they are vnfainedly welcome. This is not the maner of our age; these are no fit guests for our table; we inuite such from whom we expect some greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit; of whom we looke for extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie fauor, the great and rich men of the world, and these we glut and cram (as it were) with all maner of dainties; for these we seeke new cates, new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, new confections: but the poore ministers and other members of Christ are in so great contempt with the most,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13276:54"/> as we thinke our tables disgraced, if we admit them therunto. Wherein the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then go before vs (and we might blush thereat, if wee had not so far past the bounds of shamefastnes) who are said to haue honored their solemne feasts and bankets, with the presence of learned men, skilfull onely in the knowledge of Philosophie, according to the blindnes of that age wherein they liued.</p>
                  <p>And heere our ministers, and all other good Christians, indued with a more ful measure of Christian knowledge, than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their brethren, are to learne this good lesson, that they do not as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the most is in these daies, when they are inuited to such assemblies and meetings; fall into idle and vaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; into friuolous and vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table discourses; but that their speeches be seasoned with matter tending to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, void of offence, woorthie their persons, woorthie the hearers, woorthie the time and place where they are vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: and if <hi>Martha,</hi> that is, their deerest friends do step awrie, that they forbeare not for any respect to addresse their steps into the right way.</p>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:13276:54"/>
                  <p> But the ministers of the word are es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in this action of Christ at this time, and in this place to learne that which <hi>Paul</hi> also teacheth, that it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to their charge and dutie, <hi>To preach</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 2.</note>
                     <hi>the word, to be instant in season and out of sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to improoue, rebuke, exhort,</hi> at all times, and in all places requisite: in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, at noone, after noone, at night, at dinner time, at supper time, at all times; in the citie, in the field, in open assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, in priuat houses, in the mountains, in the deserts, by the sea side, on the sea, in publike places, in secret places, in all places. And therefore as it was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon speech with our Sauiour Christ to the people; <hi>Qui habet aures: He that hath</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 9. Mark 4. 9. Luke. 8. 8.</note>
                     <hi>eares to heare, let him heare:</hi> so likewise we find, that he gaue generall charge and commission to his disciples; <hi>Ite, praedicate:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19. Mar. 16. 15.</note>
                     <hi>Go, and preach the Gospell:</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> hath this particular commandement, euen as he tendred the loue and fauor of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster; <hi>Pasce oues: Feede my sheepe:</hi> againe, <note place="margin">Ioh. 21. 15. 16. 17.</note>
                     <hi>Peter feede:</hi> and againe; <hi>Peter feede my sheepe:</hi> noting by this earnest and pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall repetition, the care which he had, and which euerie true minister ought to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13276:55"/> haue of the peoples soules. Now what account will our idoll ministers make, that cannot feed, and our idle Non-resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that will not feede the sheepe of Christ? Or if they do, it is for orders sake onelie fower times in the yeere. If those men were appointed to haue but fower meales in the yeere for their bodily su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stenance, they would thinke their diet verie short and hard; and I thinke it no offence to wish, that such as esteem fower sermons in a whole yeere sufficient for the soules of their congregations, had no better allowance; and that those which preach not at all, were also dieted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, whereof no doubt would insue a speedie reformation.</p>
                  <p>When princes are to treat of matters of state, and of the waightie affaires of their gouernment, this charge is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to euerie man, but to such as for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turitie of iudgement and wisedome can; for trustines and fidelitie will; for bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and courage dare to sustain the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thereof. And if princes will be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with men of this sufficiencie in their worldlie affaires: how much more will the Prince of princes haue choise men to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13276:55"/> be imploied in his busines, and to be sent in his ambassage? But as princes will not acknowledge such as shall take vpon them the name and place of ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, being neither furnished with parts answerable to that calling, nor authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by them to execute the same: so we may be fully perswaded, that God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not of those dumbe dogs, who run before they are called, and go before they are sent; and being void of all good parts, are not ashamed for worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, to thrust themselues into this waightie charge. Againe, as princes will reiect the seruice of such as being suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, yet shew themselues negligent and careles in the due execution of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires committed vnto them; and go not through with their busines, but do it (as we say) by halfes, crauing audience three or fower times at the most in a whole yeere: so no doubt the Lorde approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the seruice of those messengers, whom he hath indued with gifts suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for so high a calling, and hath put knowledge into their harts, and vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into their mouthes for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; and yet consider not the waight of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13276:56"/> their charge, nor haue due regard to that which they haue taken in hand, but like idle ambassadors, lie lingring at the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cost, scarse crauing audience to do their message once in a yeere, at the most fower times; and that I doubt more for fashions sake, or for feare of the law, than for any true deuotion. Againe, as it would be no acceptable seruice vnto a prince, if his ambassador, who ought to be resident, and readie at all assaies to further his dispatches, to parle, treat, and confer vpon euerie occasion occurring, of matters tending to the publike weale of his countrie, would lie from the court, and take his pleasure in other parts, cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the managing of these affaires to another, either altogither vnskilfull or vncapable of his instructions: so may we iustly thinke, that God, who would haue his messengers to be resident among the people, to whom they are sent, to treate &amp; parle with them of their league made with him in their baptisme, and of the state of their saluation; will conceiue iust displeasure against them, if this great burden, which toucheth his honor and maiestie so neere, be by them committed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13276:56"/> to an vnskilfull hireling, that cannot cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the waightines of the cause, which he hath taken in hand, nor make due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his message when audience shal be granted vnto him.</p>
                  <p>Againe, as Princes woulde (and that iustly) mislike with their ambassadours, and account them little better than trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that for feare of displeasure, or to deserue fauor of a forren prince, woulde omit the principal point, and head of his message, touching the honor of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the securitie of his state: so let all those who haue vndertaken this charge vnder God, fully make their rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning to be cast out of their Lord and masters fauor, like traitors and rebels, if they shall conceale any part of their mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, which toucheth the honor and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie of him that sent them.</p>
                  <p>Now while Christ is thus occupied in preaching to <hi>Marie,</hi> the text saith that <hi>Martha is carefull, and troubled about many things.</hi> And what are these things? Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no other things, (as may be gathered by circumstances) than houshold affairs, and (as I saide before) the dressing, and preparing of Christs dinner; a matter in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13276:57"/> shewe very necessary and tolerable, and the more, bicause (perhaps) they coulde not otherwise be conueniently perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without hir presence and labor; and yet we see that Christ alloweth not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in any sort. If then this care of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> escapeth not without rebuke at Christs hands, in a matter which carieth some good shew of excuse: how much more do the incessant cares, &amp; continual troubles, which wicked worldlings take, &amp; sustaine, not once, like <hi>Martha,</hi> but al the daies of their life, &amp; as if they should liue for euer, deserue to be reprooued? <hi>Martha</hi> had respect vnto Christs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment; they onely regard themselues, and their profit: <hi>Marthas</hi> care extendeth to matters of smaller moment; their care is how they may wickedly compas great and mightie things: <hi>Marthas</hi> care sauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not of any sauing, or pinching hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, their care is, how they may heape vp wealth, and scrape riches togither: <hi>Marthas</hi> care hurteth none but hir selfe, in regard of hir slacknes; their care hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth themselues and other, for many cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Themselues, by reason of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vexation, which they haue in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13276:57"/> getting; the feare and perplexitie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are possessed, in keeping, and the tortures, and torments which they endure in spending: others, bicause by their worldly carefulnes, they study how they may by all sinister meanes, and bad practises, deceiue euen their deerest friends, to make themselues either migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or wealthie; two forcible motiues, which often carie men away violentlie from Christ, yea so far sometimes, that they neuer returne againe. Of the one, <hi>Iudas</hi> may serue for an example; of the <note place="margin">Matth. 26. 15. 16. 1. Sam. 19.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; 22. 7. 8.</note> other, <hi>Saul</hi> may be vnto vs a fit patterne; <hi>Iudas</hi> sold his master for money; and <hi>Saul</hi> persecuted <hi>Dauid</hi> with great care, and trauell, the better therby to establish his tottering throne.</p>
                  <p>No pretence then serueth, to prefer the care of worldly causes, before the hearing of the word. It is no current ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse, to say: I haue bidden strangers to dinner, nay I haue inuited Christ to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, therefore I can not come; or to saie with those in the Gospell; <hi>I haue maried a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 14. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 19. 20.</note>
                     <hi>wife; I haue bought fiue yoke of oxen; I haue bought a farme, and therefore I cannot come:</hi> Yet thus do our worldlings now a daies
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:13276:58"/> excuse their slacknes, and thinke that they haue sufficiently discharged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. We may, nay we ought in dutie, to loue our wiues wel; but so, as our loue <note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 25. Col. 3. 19.</note> towards Christ waxe not colde. We may buy farmes, oxen, marchandize, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form al other actions agreeable with our vocation &amp; calling; but so, as thereby we be not drawen, and intised to neglect our soules health, and to thinke that hower lost, which is bestowed in hearing of the word. We may be in some measure care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of our busines; but we must not be ouer-carefull, which is for the most part accompanied with distrust in gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, as if times, and seasons, and meanes, being in his hands, and at his disposition; he were not able to giue suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse to our labours, vnlesse we did tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and vexe our selues, and become slacke in his busines in regarde of our owne. The verie heathen heerin accuse vs, and without repentance shall rise in iudgement against vs, at that dreadfull day, who learned onely by the blind light of philosophie, to contemne the things of the world, &amp; to prefer humain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, before the rich treasure of kings,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13276:58"/> refusing the great preferments of court, that they might the more freely, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally, attende their studies. <hi>Diogenes</hi> cared more to meditate in his tub, on the mysteries of philosophy, than to ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle in silkes in <hi>Alexanders</hi> pallace idlie. And <hi>Aristippus</hi> seeing the great cares wherewith he was possessed, and dangers wherin he liued in his nauigation; threw his money into the sea, with these words; I had rather loose thee, than that for thee <hi>Aristippus</hi> shoulde be lost. What woulde these men haue done, if they had beene inlightned with the true knowledge of the worde? These examples with manie others, are enregistred, and committed to eternall memorie, to the shame of Christians, who hunt after these glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring things with great greedines, and spend the greatest part of their care, stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, meditations and endeuors, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chase momentane riches, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme some glorious, or rather vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious actions, forgetting this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Christ: <hi>First seeke the kingdome</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 6. 33.</note>
                     <hi>of God, and the righteousnes thereof, and all these things shall be cast vpon you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if neither necessarie care, in our
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:13276:59"/> houshold causes, nor vnnecessarie, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, tending to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our estates, in wealth, or credite, be allowed of our Sauiour Christ, when there is question of hearing of his word: thē what iudgment remaineth for those, who hauing no pretence, no colour to hide their wilfull negligence, in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, do voluntarily absent themselues from the exercises of religion, choosing rather to liue idlie at home, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely abroad, than to frequent ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and places of publike praier, wher the sweete foode of their soules is offred <hi>gratis</hi> vnto them?</p>
                  <p>Thus we see how far the bounds of Christian care ought to extend; thus we see how far <hi>Martha</hi> should haue beene carefull; thus we see how far we also may be carefull in our owne causes.</p>
                  <p>Now we finde not in the course of the text, that <hi>Martha</hi> being thus sharpely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked of Christ, murmured, or grudged thereat; which taxeth the rebellious and insolent humors that abound in this our age, among the crooked and peruerse generation: wherin it seemeth that our soares are so ful of corruption, so festred,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13276:59"/> and growen to such a head, as they will not endure to be touched; much lesse abide the surgeon to launce them, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie holesome remedies to cure them. If the well affected minister, like the good surgeon, do but offer to put his launce to our soares, we straight waies (as it is in the Prouerbs) wince like galled horses; we spurne against the prophets of the Lord; generall reprehensions, are made particular accusations, and slanders, and almost no man examineth his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science; no man entreth into his owne hart, which no doubt is a thousand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses against him; but like the dog, we bite the stone, in steed of him that threw it, that is; we bite, we torment the poore ministers of Christ, when as in deed our malice reacheth euen to Christ himselfe, whose words they vtter, and cast them foorth like stones, against the currish and doggish obstinacie of the wicked: and we are so much ouercome with gall and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred against them, when we feele our gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie consciences galled by them, when we heare our filthy corruptions discouered, and the manifold pollutions of our oug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie sins laid open, that we could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13276:60"/> like <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> wife, to weare <hi>Tullies</hi> toong in our hats, bicause he spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to blaze the dronkennes, and some other imperfections wherewith that man was stained. But although our <hi>Tullies,</hi> that is, our ministers loose their toongs, though <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> go headlesse, <note place="margin">Mat. 14. 10. Mark. 6. 27. 2. Kin. 22. 27</note> to please <hi>Herods</hi> minion, though <hi>Miche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> eate and drinke the bread and water of affliction, though <hi>Stephen</hi> be stoned, <note place="margin">Act. 7. 58. Act. 13. 50. &amp; 2. vers. 3. Act. 3. 4. Act. 14. 19.</note> though <hi>Paule</hi> and other faithfull labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in the Lords haruest be persecuted to the death, imprisoned, banished, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured and tormented: yet ought they to <hi>Crie aloud, and not to spare, to lift vp their</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Isai. 58. 1.</note>
                     <hi>voices like trumpets, &amp; to shew the people their transgressions, and the house of Iacob their sinnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is now time to looke into the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, which containeth the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or comendation of <hi>Maries</hi> choise; where first before we enter into the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities, this general note occurreth, that as reproofe is necessarie for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement of our errors: so commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is also profitable, for our farther incouragement in well dooing, that we
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13276:60"/> may resolutely proceed in our well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted course, and grow from strength to strength, and from vertue to vertue, vntill the full finishing of our race.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Laudatáque virtus</l>
                     <l>Crescit. &amp; immensum gloria calcar habet.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Saith the Poet:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>By commendation vertue is increast,</l>
                     <l>And glories spur doth take but litle rest.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And although this alacritie ought to be in euery good Christian; to go forward without any spur: yet our dulnes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be stirred vp, and we begin to languish, and waxe wearie in any good course, if praise accompanie not our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but this being the true, and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided companion of godlines, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as the shadow is of the body; our commendation will bring vs the greater contentment, and satisfaction, if we haue regard onely to the consideration of our dueties in all our proceedings. <hi>Bonum est laudari, sed praestantius esse lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem,</hi> saith <hi>Seneca:</hi> it is a good thing to be praised, but far better to be praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthy. Let <hi>Mary</hi> heare Christ, and <hi>Mary</hi> shall haue this honor, euen the praise of Christ him selfe; and that is a
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13276:61"/> singular honor in deede, which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from the honored: but that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation carieth small credit, which commeth from a lewd or vitious person; and in my iudgement, that mans reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is rather diminished than augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that hath no better blazer of his good parts. The circumstances then meete to be considered in this point, are these; the party praising, the party pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, the cause, and ground of this praise. The party praising, ought to be such a one, as hauing the vertues, godly dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, and incorrupt iudgement which belong to an honest man, may adde cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and estimation both to him selfe, and to him whom he graceth with his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: for we see oftentimes how much partialitie, and affection preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in these cases, which causeth vs to looke narrowly into the parts deseruing praise, and to winke careleslie at manie things, which obscure, and ouershadowe all the rest; and who is there almost, that is not caried away with a conceit of the least gift, which maketh him to shine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so little, aboue his fellowes? Euerie man is giuen to flatter himselfe, and to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13276:61"/> make the most of nothing; and as praise is an ordinarie, and certaine companion of vertue: so is pride likewise attendant vpon praise; and being somewhat too fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar therewith, laboureth to giue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue also the checke-mate. Howe much therefore discretion is requisite in that man which commendeth another; may hereby easely appeere. And no lesse mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, with humblenes of spirit, is to be desired in him to whom praise is ascribed, otherwise, he will set vp his pecocks plumes, and fall as far in loue with himselfe, as did <hi>Narcissus</hi> with his owne shadowe, which in the ende will worke his miserable ruine.</p>
                  <p>Selfe-conceit is a dangerous humor, and not to be tempered but with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, which maketh vs to refer all those good things, all those godlie motions, which are in vs, vnto Christ, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the weaknes, blindnes, and ignorance of flesh and blood, without the assistance of his spirit.</p>
                  <p>The cause and ground of this praise is also to be considered, prudence, iustice, temperance, chastitie, liberalitie, and such other vertues, haue their due prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13276:62"/> but to heare the word of God, the cause of all goodnes, and as it were the spring whence all vertues are deriued, is the thing which Christ commendeth in <hi>Marie,</hi> and recommendeth vnto all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie. <hi>Achitophel</hi> that spiteful and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious enimie of <hi>Dauid,</hi> was wife; theeues <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 23.</note> in the diuision of their booties, seeme to obserue a kind of iustice; the Pharisie is strict in his conuersation, a great imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of morall vertue, and as it is in the Gospell, <hi>Fasteth twise a weeke,</hi> which is the part of temperance; giueth tithe of all <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 10, 11, 12.</note> that he hath, which belongeth to iustice; goeth to the temple to praie, which ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth (at the least) a shew of zeale and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: but <hi>Achitophels</hi> wisedome was worldlie, full of mischiefe, and void of all deuotion: the theeues thinke on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lesse in parting the spoile, than on iustice, nay they are then come to the highest point of iniustice: the Pharisies zeale, and other vertues are nothing but hypocrisie and selfe-conceit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 13.</note> so far from deseruing praise, as they are sequestred and excluded from the true cause, from whence true praise ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth.</p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:13276:62"/>
                  <p> But let vs now come to <hi>Marie,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the causes and reasons, for the which Christ attributeth vnto hir this great commendation. What doth she? how doth she bestow hir time, while hir sister <hi>Martha</hi> attendeth hir houshold bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sines? We find in the text, that <hi>She sate at Iesus feet, and heard his preaching:</hi> which is that good part which he meaneth she had chosen. She sitteth at his feete, she heareth, she heareth the word: by sitting, note hir diligence; by hearing, marke hir attention; by hearing the word, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hir deuotion. It is a token of a good scholler to haue so great affection to his masters instructions, as may mooue him with earnest desire to presse neere vnto the place where he teacheth: and it is not ynough for vs to be in place where our master Christ is, but we must vse all diligence to be neere vnto him; yea if it be possible, with <hi>Marie</hi> to sit at his feete: for if it were sufficient to be in place where he is, then <hi>Martha</hi> had not been blamed, who was in the same house. To stand aloofe, and not to labour to come neerer, is an argument of great slacknes and negligence: and these three
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13276:63"/> things, diligence in comming; attention in hearing; and zeale in imbracing the word, are so linked togither, and so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily depend ech of the other, as the one being taken away, the rest cannot possibly subsist. We must come, &amp; come to heare, and heare to follow: to come, and not to heare is vaine; to heare, and not to follow is damnable: <hi>For not the hearers onely, but the doers of the word are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 13. Luk. 7. 21. Iames 1. 22.</note> Then let vs so come that we may heare, and so heare that we may follow: that comming, hearing, and following, <hi>we may follow the lambe wheresoeuer he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and enter into those ioies which he hath prepared for his elect. Faith</hi> (saith S. <hi>Paul) commeth by hearing;</hi> and how shal we heare <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 17</note> vnles we haue accesse to the place where Christ speaketh? And how shall we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand his voice, vnles we presse neere vnto him? Then how shall we haue faith whereby we are saued, vnles we presse neere to sit at Iesus feete? To compasse the least worldlie matter without dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence we cannot, and with diligence the greatest things may be performed; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence deuoureth all difficulties, and the hardest actions seeme easie vnto vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13276:63"/> If there be question of purchasing a Diademe or crowne, how do we extend all our forces? how do we labor and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell for the same? The desire of honor findeth no let; the opinion of fame cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs through the pikes; the thirst of gaine, feareth no gulfe, no rock, no tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest, no danger. In these matters no dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence wanteth; we go, we run, we ride, we poste, we presse, we thrust to come in place where these transitorie things may be found: and shall we then draw backe our feet, or be negligent to find out the hidden treasure, and pretious pearle of the word, <hi>which is to be desired more than</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 19. 10.</note>
                     <hi>gold, yea than fine gold; sweeter also than honie, or the honie comb;</hi> which promiseth &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto vs that incorruptible crown, which no man can take from vs? This cannot be found without seeking, and Christ himselfe hath spoken the word, that <hi>If we seeke, we shall find.</hi> It is also said <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 7.</note> that <hi>Marie</hi> heard. She did not as I feare manie among vs do; vouchsafe Christ the presence of their bodies, and let their eares go on pilgrimage, and set their minds on their halfe-penie: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie part of hir was (as it were) dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13276:64"/> to that holie action. Heere let euerie estate &amp; degree enter into their consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and examine themselues, if they haue deuoted all the parts of their bodie to this office, when they haue been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent at sermons. Let the marchant looke whether his mind hath not been in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren parts about his aduentures, or at home in his shop or seller, about his commodities: let the lawier consider, whether he hath not thought vpon his clients causes, or inuented shifts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the widow and fatherles: let arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of what trade soeuer; let all other of what qualitie or condition soeuer, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, base, high, low, rich, poore, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber whether worldlie cogitations haue not drawen away their eares at anie time from the hearing of the word. Attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the sister of meditation; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meditation, the word passeth awaie and becommeth vnprofitable vnto vs: It entreth in at the one eare, and goeth out at the other. Hypocrites will vouchsafe to be present somtimes at sermons, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bleare the eies of the world with a pretence of holines: but we cannot saie that hypocrits do lend their eares to the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13276:64"/> preachers, to their good admonitions and wholesome doctrine, or if they do, that it is for any deuotion. The Scribes and Pharisies follow Christ as well as the rest of the people, they enter into the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogs, they heare him dispute, they heare him teach; but it is to intrap him; <note place="margin">Luke. 6. 7.</note> it is to take som aduantage against him; it is not for anie affection they beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, or his doctrine: and therefore it is not ynough to be present; it is not y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to heare; but a third thing, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and zeale is also required. With this deuotion and zeale did <hi>Marie</hi> heare, as one hungering and thirsting more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteousnes, than carefull of hir owne dinner, or Christs intertainment; whereof the approbation and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Christ himselfe may be a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient witnes. For if hir deuotion had been cold, and not in full measure, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as it were burning like fire within hir; <hi>Marie</hi> might haue pretended, nay she had diuers causes to mooue hir at that time otherwise to imploy hir selfe: first, in respect of Christ, the better to prouide for his intertainment, and the rather bicause he vouchsafed to visit that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13276:65"/> house so willingly; as also for that it see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth he came on the sudden; next, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of hir sister <hi>Martha,</hi> who needed hir assistance, being not able to dispatch all things alone; as likewise that she might not minister offence vnto hir by sitting still, without regard of the great paines which she saw hir to take. But none of these considerations coulde diuert hir from hir dutie, or make hir to forsake that better part which she had chosen. And therfore hir sister grieued therwith, as imputing some negligence and want of naturall affection in hir, entereth into an expostulation against hir; but Christ taketh vpon him to defend hir cause: where we may note by the waie, that if the causes are iust &amp; religious which we take in hand, the Lord wil maintaine thē against all pretences, against all expostu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, whether of enimie or friend.</p>
                  <p>None of the former considerations, could make <hi>Marie</hi> to start an inch from hir place: which giueth vs this profitable lesson, that being entred into this good course of religion, and pietie; we should persist, and go forward therein, and not decline from the same, for any worldlie
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13276:65"/> respect whatsoeuer. The busines, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this life, (I confesse) are manie, and may mooue vs very much: but they must not remooue vs in any case from hearing of the word; our sisters and kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folks are, and may be (no doubt) deere vnto vs; but Christ will haue vs to <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 37. Luk. 14. 26. Mat. 16. 24, 25, 26. Luk. 9. 23, 24, 25, 26.</note>
                     <hi>father, and mother, sister, and brother,</hi> and those things which we haue in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test estimation, to follow him. Oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities are not to be neglected; let vs heare Christ while we may, haplie when we would we shall not. <hi>Marie</hi> (no doubt) had this consideration, that he was to go about his fathers busines, that he vsed not to soiorne longin one place, that he was to communicate his gifts, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to manie, that the ignorant, poore, blinde, lame, and diseased of other parts, and of other countries had like desire, and need of his presence; and therefore she tooke the time while it was offered. Perhaps some other time might haue beene found, for his better entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (and Christ is not so curious a guest, as many of our great; naie meane men are) but it might be doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther so fit a time, or place, woulde haue
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13276:66"/> beene againe presented for the hearing of the word: and therefore <hi>Marie</hi> verie wisely, and religiously, imbraced the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent occasion, vsing the benefit thereof to hir great comfort, and consolation.</p>
                  <p>And here I might iustly taxe the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our age, which omitteth no occasions, which seemeth neuer wearie, to heare friuolous discourses, or vaine tales, of I know not what prophane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: but these men are no sooner in the church, but they seeme to be as it were cloied, and to haue taken a surfet of the doctrine of Christ, and his ministers: they that can be content to stande with paine many houres, at idle pastimes, are loth to sit at ease, one houre at a sermon: they that presse neere, and are most at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to heare idle communication; stand a far off, at religious and godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises, so as it may appeere, that they carie verie slender deuotion thereunto. Let the guilty conscience examine it self, and amend by the example of <hi>Marie;</hi> of whom it is added in the text, that <hi>she had chosen the good part;</hi> which increaseth greatly hir commendation. For to be compelled to heare Christ, is not thanks-woorthy,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13276:66"/> and if in performing any good office of curtesie or humanitie to our friends, it is the more acceptable when it proceedeth frō a man voluntarily with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intreatie, without long expectation, without constraint; and <hi>Bis dat qui citò dat:</hi> He giueth twise that giueth quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: much more will the Lord esteeme of those offices of pietie &amp; godlines, which are performed towards him, with al wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling readines, and readie willingnes. A point which condemneth the recusants of our time, who are so far from choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing this good part, that they vtterly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse and abhor to visit our holie exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, excluding, and as it were banishing themselues from the presence of Christ, and consequently from the ioies of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                  <p>Let vs now looke more particularly into the words of our Sauior Christ, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the word. <hi>One thing</hi> (saith he) <hi>is needfull; Marie hath chosen the good part, which shall not be taken from hir.</hi> Wherein three especiall things may be obserued. First, the necessitie of the word; next, the excellencie thereof; then, the assurance of the continuance of the same, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13276:67"/> to those that religiously imbrace it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Martha,</hi> as we haue alreadie heard, was busied about manie things, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning matter of houshold, forgetting the principall, which concerned hir soules health, and therefore as Christ reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth hir vnnecessarie carefulnes; so he putteth hir in mind of a more necessarie point omitted by hir. I see a large field of discourse, offred by these three obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, but I wil not extend my cōceits so far, as may bring foorth more paine vnto me in writing, than profit to those that shall read the same. And bicause I find the necessitie and the excellencie of the word, to haue so neere affinitie, as he that granteth the one, cannot denie the other, for the mutuall correspondencie which is betweene them, I will be bold to confound them togither, and yet I trust without anie great confusion, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing to shew the excellencie by the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitie, and the necessitie by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie.</p>
                  <p>Now the necessitie and excellencie of any thing, is seen in nothing better than in the effects, in the fruits and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which it produceth. And what can
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13276:67"/> bring foorth better effects, better fruits, better commodities than the worde of God? It chaseth away the mist &amp; clouds of darknes; it openeth the eies of our vnderstanding; it inlighteneth our minds <note place="margin">Psal. 19. 8</note> as the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> testifieth: and are not these notable effects? Our minds being inlightened, it maketh vs to enter into our consciences; it displaieth the vglines of our sinnes; it giueth vs a true feeling and remorse of them; and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuerteth our soules vnto the Lord: <note place="margin">Psal. 19. 7</note> and are not these notable effects? Being conuerted to the Lord, it intertaineth vs in his good fauor; it teacheth vs to walk <note place="margin">Ibid. v. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Deut. 29</note> in his waies; it conducteth vs in the right path, and directeth our steps euen to the place of eternal blisse: and are not these notable effects? It is the spirituall suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance <note place="margin">Deut. 8.</note> whereby we liue; the sinewes of our soules, yea life it selfe, without the which we are as dead, and sleepe in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting death: and are not these notable effects? That we are regenerated and <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1</note> become new borne babes; that the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall corruption and filth of our first parents is not imputed vnto vs; that we are washed and clensed from our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:13276:68"/> and presented pure and vnspotted before the tribunall seate of God: is an effect of the word. That the burden of our sinnes, which oppressed vs, is made easie; that we feele inward comfort in <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>r. 15. 16.</note> our soules; that we sing <hi>Alleluya</hi> with the saints in the congregation, and reioice <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>sal. 19. 8.</note> in the spirit vnto the Lord: is an effect of the word. That we are ioined with <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>h. 15. 4. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>m. 8. 17.</note> God; that wee are fellow-heires with Christ our eldest brother, of the celestial in heritance, and shall after this transito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie life, be put in full possession thereof: is an effect of the word: Then who can denie that the word is both necessarie and excellent? If without it we liue in blindnes and error; if vnder the compas of condemnation; wandring in the vale and shadow of death; out of the fauor of God; hunger-starued in our soules; most vglie and monstrous creatures, void of comfort and consolation, abiects and fugitiues from the presence of the Lord; and falling headlong into the pit of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting destruction: who can denie that the word is both necessarie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent?</p>
                  <p>This worde hath manie names in the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:13276:68"/> Scripture, which do euerie of them as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well illustrate, and set foorth the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, as also shew vnto vs the necessitie thereof: In Deuter. it is called Manna: In Exodus, a Carbuncle; <hi>Amos</hi> termeth it <note place="margin">Deut. 8. 3. Exo. 28. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Amos 8. Esaie 9. 2. Ier. 23. 29. Mich. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Psal. 119. 105. Psal. 23. 4. Mat. 13. 4<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Luke 9. 6 Rom. 1. 1 Ephe. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Bread; <hi>Esay</hi> Light; <hi>Ieremie</hi> a Fire; <hi>Miche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> an iron Horne; <hi>Dauid</hi> a Lanterne vnto our feete, the Rod of strength, the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Gods kingdome, the Way of life; In <hi>Matthew</hi> it is a Treasure; In <hi>Luke,</hi> a Plough wherewith the church is tilled; <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it the power of God, the Helmet of saluation, the Sworde of the spirit. It were almost an infinite labour to search out and set downe the seuerall appellations of the worde in Scripture; and to discourse vpon them all, were a worke altogither without end: yet shall they not all be passed ouer with silence, bicause some briefe explication, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of some of them, will serue much to confirme that vnto the faithles generation, whereof no good Christian will euer make any doubt, for that in the word, we finde this of the word. It is a Carbuncle, and what is the nature of a Carbuncle? To yeeld most cleer light, euen in the darkest &amp; obscurest places.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:13276:69"/> Againe, it is a Lanterne vnto our feete, and a Light vnto our steps, which in sense, concurreth with the other. And where is the Carbuncle, where is Light, where is the Lanterne needful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable? In darkenes; where is this darkenes? In the worlde; what is the world? Truelie a most miserable dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and pit of palpable darknes, euen as thicke as that of Aegypt, wherein are most dangerous stumbling blocks, most deepe gulfes, most intricate and endles labirinthes, which the deuill our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie hath laid, to entrap, and enwrap vs, that being once fallen, we should neuer rise againe. But this light of the worde, hath discouered them all vnto vs, and like <hi>Ariadnes</hi> threed, doth guide and conduct vs, out of the maze, wherin that cruell and greedie <hi>Minotaure</hi> lurketh, readie to deuour those that wander ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so little out of the way. In this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral darknes, what greater comfort can arriue to him, who either at home or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad goeth he knoweth not whether, than a lanterne to direct him in his course, and to addresse him in the right path? If we go but downe a paire of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:13276:69"/> staires, or ouer a threshold, how timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouslie do we set our feet to the ground? Howe carefully do wee grope with our hands, and make them as it were buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to defend our faces; at euery step we be carefull of sure footing, and at euerie newe step, we feare the next, doubting some danger. But these dangers are not so certaine, as in that spirituall darknes, for at euery step there is a stop, and to helpe vs forward, that we may the more easely fall, sathan maketh the way slippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and myrie, that falling we may not easely recouer our selues. But that we may perceiue his snares, and auoid them, God hath giuen vnto vs his word, a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to our feete, and a light to our pathes, which worde, <hi>Dauid</hi> also calleth the rod of strength; and direction to stay and vphold vs that our feet slip not. In darke and slipperie places, to haue the benefite of light is a great helpe, and comfort; but not onely to haue light, to see the blockes that lie in our way; but also a staffe, to sustaine our weaknes, is a singular blessing. To him that trauelleth on the land, in a mistie and clowdy day, and in an vnknowen place, a guide can
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13276:70"/> neuer be vnwelcome, bicause the danger of beasts, the hazard of theeues, and (if nothing else) the vnpleasantnes of that solitarie progresse, will not a little dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may him. To him that trauelleth on the sea, in a strange coste, without direction of carde or compasse, when by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of winde, waues, and fogs, he hath as it were lost himselfe; a good and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert pilot must needs be very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The state of vs that liue in this world, is altogither like vnto the state of the traueller, or of the mariner, and the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guide, the onely pilote, to direct our course, whereby we may auoide the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perils, which hang ouer our heads, is the word of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>But this is not all: it is not onelie a lanterne to light vs, a staffe to staie vs, a pilote, and guide to conduct vs out of dangers; nay the verie way it selfe; but it is also a sword, an helmet, a complete harnes of proofe, to withstand the force of the enimie, to resist the firie darts of sathan, and to tame his vnbrideled rage. It is a poeticall fable, but not without some sense, that <hi>Thetis</hi> dipped hir sonne <hi>Achilles</hi> in the riuer Stix, whereby his
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:13276:70"/> bodie might be made (if I may so saie) impenetrable; and yet <hi>Achilles</hi> was not so safe, but <hi>Paris</hi> could wound him treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously, in the sole of the foote: but we are so dipped in the blood of that imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate lambe, Christ Iesus; so armed and defended with the sworde of the worde, the shield of faith, the helmet of saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Epses. 6. 14, 15, 16.</note> the brest-plate of righteousnes, and shod with the shooes of the preparation of the Gospell; as if we stand fast, like good soldiers, vnder the banner of our captaine Christ, and vse the weapons which he hath giuen vnto vs: the force of the strongest enimies, nay thousands of enimies, nay the very gates of hell it selfe shall not preuaile against vs. The diuel may nibble at our heele, but he shal neuer come so neere, to wound the sole <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> of our foote, or touch the least haire of our head: but if we shall negligently put off any part of this complete harnes, we shall foorthwith lie open to that maine enimie of our soules; and being wilie, he will take his aduantage against vs, and being also mightie, he will ouercome vs, and reduce vs to a most miserable serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, both of bodie and soule. This word
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:13276:71"/> is also called Manna, and bread, in other places of Scripture; shewing that as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bread, and sustenance, it is impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for vs to subsist in this world: so our soules should be miserablie hunger star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, without this spirituall foode: and as bread maketh strong the hart of man, as the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> speaketh: so the word <note place="margin">Psa. 104. 15.</note> is the strength, and as it were the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of our soules. And as he that will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain his health, and life in this world, must receiue bread into his mouth, and not onely receiue it, but also chew it, and swallow it into his stomacke, that being there digested, it may be conuerted into holesome nutriment: so he that desireth to liue for euer, must not onely receiue the worde with his eares, but also em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, and let it enter into his hart, and meditating theron, digest the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable doctrine, and profitablie apply it vnto his souls health. And as when we haue digested that portion of breade which we haue eaten, we presentlie feele a newe appetite, which calleth for newe sustenance: so must we without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, by hearing, meditation, &amp; prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, satisfie the stomacke of our soules,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:13276:71"/> hungring and thirsting after righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And is it true, that there is such a proportion, and analogie between tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and spirituall food? Then in what miserable estate are they, that may, and yet refuse to feede their soules with that heauenly Manna? As likewise they that are, or ought to be the good stewardes thereof, to breake and deuide this bread of life vnto the people, but take verie slender care to performe this dutie. But of this inough alreadie.</p>
                  <p>The worde is also called a pearle, or <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 44</note> treasure, for the which we ought to sell al that we haue, that we may be therby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to buie the same. For it, we must not spare our best iewels, we must not spare our richest bags, nay we must not spare our deerest blood. And if nothing <note place="margin">Reu. 12. 11</note> ought to seeme too precious, nothing too costlie, nothing too deere, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of this treasure: what treasure; what iewell; what siluer or gold shall we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer before it? That, is as the dust &amp; drosse of the earth: this, a most perfect, and pure quintessence, yea puritie and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection it selfe; that, is subiect to alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, corruption, losse, and danger of fire,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:13276:72"/> water, theeues, and many other hazards; this, is euer one, immutable, constant, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 25. Psal. 33. 11. Psa. 119. 89.</note> with them, &amp; within them that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, &amp; neuer to be taken from them. I will not stande to make any particular application of the other appellations of the worde, these few may suffice to shewe vnto vs the necessity &amp; excellency therof, according to my first purpose. In sum, if things of greatest continuance, are to be preferred before brittle &amp; momentanie things; if things whereof greatest good ariseth, before those that yeeld little, or none at al; if things pure and incorrupt, before those that are full of pollution; if things pleasant and comfortable, before those that bring little or no true conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: then let the worde of God, be iustly preferred before all things, bicause there is nothing that for these respects can match therewith.</p>
                  <p>Let vs now come to the assurance of the continuance of this worde, in these words of our Sauiour, <hi>which shall not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from hir.</hi> The continuance of the word <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 25. Mat. 24. 25.</note> is euerlasting, and world without ende; <hi>Heauen and earth shall passe away,</hi> (saith <note place="margin">Mar. 13. 31.</note> Christ) <hi>but my words shall not passe away:</hi> but
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:13276:72"/> those onely shall reape the benefite, and comfort thereof in the world, that carie a sound affection, and true deuotion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the same. If we follow it; it will follow vs, and we shall haue a full measure and portion thereof: Christ will come to our <note place="margin">Ioh. 19. 23.</note> houses, he will dwell with vs, he will visit <hi>Marie,</hi> and instruct hir in the way of truth, and saluation. But if like wanton children, we shall cast this bread of life vnder our feet, as if we were cloied ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; if we shall begin to bite our nurses teate; that is to say, vse hard measure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ministers, who like good and tender nurses deliuer the sweete milke of the worde vnto vs, (a matter too rife in these daies:) we must looke for the like measure at Gods hands, who will not faile to correct our wantonnes, and to chastise such corne-fed children; yea he will take their bread from them, and giue it to those hungrie soules, to whom it will be better welcome. Then shall we <note place="margin">Amos 8. 12.</note> wander from sea to sea, and from the North euen vnto the East; then shall we run too and fro, to seeke the worde, and shall not finde it.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore to conclude, if we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:13276:73"/> care of our soules, any commiserati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the wretched estate wherein we stand; let it appeere by som better fruits, that we burn with a feruent zeale of the word; that we reuerence and honor it; that we prefer it before all temporall things whatsoeuer. Let the people shew their earnest deuotion to heare; let the ministers shew their willing readines to teach; and both an vnfained desire to follow, and put in practise that which is heard and taught: let both (I say) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the performance of ech Christian dutie; let the people heare, and heare of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and heare attentiuely, and practise effectually: let the ministers preach, and preach often, and preach sincerely, and practise effectually: for as the coldnes of the people in hearing shall receiue a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie iudgement; so the slacknes of the minister in preaching shall not escape vnpunished. God grant a full measure of perfect deuotion in hearer and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that the word may abide and dwell in vs, and bring foorth such plentifull fruit, as may make vs acceptable vnto the Lord, in that great day when euerie man shal be called to account for his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:13276:73"/> and receiue such reward as is due to profitable, or vnprofitable seruants: at what time he will diuide the sheepe from the goats; the one to his right hande, the other to his left; the one to iustice, the other to mercie; the one to ioy, the other to torments; the one to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting condemnation in hel fire with the diuell and his ministers; the other to perpetuall glorie in heauen with the blessed Saints, Angels, Archangels, and the rest of those celestiall citizens, there to sing praise vnto the Lambe which sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the throne, for euer.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:74"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:74"/>
                  <p> A BRIEFE DISCOVRSE intituled A BVCKLER AGAINST A SPANISH BRAG: Written vpon the first <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the intended inua-</hi>sion, and now not <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither vnmeet to</hi> be published.</p>
                  <p>1588</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13276:75"/>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:13276:75"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>GOod Reader, this short discourse follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was penned when the rumor of the Spanish inuasiō was first dispersed; which I did then forbear to publish for som particular causes. But now being mooued for dutifull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderations to present the two former to that good Ladie: I thought it not amisse; hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered some thing in the first copie, to ioine this also vnto them, and to offer the same to thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous acceptation. It is verie true that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of season in respect of the action: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles considering that the enimie carieth still the same mind towards vs, and that he is not so repulsed with dishonor; so departed with disgrace; so ouerwhelmed in the sea; &amp; disper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by Gods mightie power with intollerable losse and dammage; but his inueterate malice, and our sinnes may cause fresh supplies to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: as likewise that such meditations are profitable not only against those Spanish threts and attempts; but also against the practises of all other aduersaries of his nature, qualitie and disposition, wherof there are manie, which looke askew, and with an enuious eie vpon the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous &amp; florishing estate of our sacred Prince,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:13276:76"/> Countrie, and Religion: I haue presumed to offer vnto thee this <hi>BVCKLER</hi> against all his, and their future brags and malicious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises. I know the zealous minister hath and doth deliuer vnto thee daily bucklers of perfect proofe: vse theirs, and neglect not this in thy like occasions: Theirs are of better proof, bicause they are of better skill: yet maist thou find somwhat heerein wherewith to defend thy selfe. If thou shalt accept thereof, it will encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me to endeuor to prepare some better and stronger weapon, when any iust cause shall be presented. Farewell.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>E. R.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:13276:76"/>
                  <head>A briefe Discourse intituled, A BVCKLER AGAINST A SPANISH BRAG: Written vpon the first rumor of the <hi>intended inuasion, and now not</hi> altogither vnmeete to <hi>be published.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE rumor of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uasiō soundeth no doubt vnpleasant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the eares of those, that haue manie yeeres liued in peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie, and may at the first not a little discomfort the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setled and faint courage. But vpon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter consideration of the goodnes of the cause to be defended; the necessitie of resistance; the dangers that may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred; the nature and disposition of the enimie; with other like circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: the weakest begin to take hart, and to arme themselues aginst al euents. And this is a very good resolution, and woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:13276:77"/> great cōmendation; wherin that we may be the better cōfirmed &amp; encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged now in this threatning time: I haue presumed to offer this short discourse, as a <hi>Buckler,</hi> vnto euerie good Christian and faithfull soldier of our nation; the vse wherof may be in some measure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and comfortable vnto them; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of a consideration of our state, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of religion and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wisedome, with some remedie against the intended mischiefe. Wherein (that we may proceed with some order) we will consider two things: the one, <hi>Who we are,</hi> (I meane the faithfull;) the other, <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whose banner and conduct we fight.</hi> We are the <hi>workmanship of the highest, created</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psa. 119. 73. Gen. 2. 26. 27. Mat. 10. 30. Luk. 12. 7.</note>
                     <hi>after his owne image</hi> and likenes; <hi>whose haires he hath numbred,</hi> and will not suffer one of them to fall without his especiall prouidence. And if he taketh care of the haires of our head; how much more hath he regard of the conseruation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and blood of his Saints? whereof one drop is more pretious than manie thousand haires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A sparrow falleth not to the ground,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lords direction; wee are more <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 29.</note>
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:13276:77"/> deere vnto him than all the sparrowes in the world, and therefore why should we be discouraged? If the least woorms and senseles creatures are vnder his protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; how much more are they whom he hath vouchsafed this great honor <hi>to be</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 20. 36. Iohn. 1. 12. Galat. 3. 26. Rom. 8. 17.</note>
                     <hi>made like vnto himselfe:</hi> yea <hi>sonnes,</hi> and <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-heires</hi> with his sonne of the celestiall inheritance. If we are his sonnes, then is he our father; if our father, then vnles we be graceles imps and disobedient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, he will not faile to performe the part of a good father vnto vs. Our earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fathers do it, much more will our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie <note place="margin">Matth 7. 9. 10. 11. Rom. 8. 32. Iohn. 3. 16.</note> father: hee that spared not the blood of his owne and onely sonne to saue our soules from the bondage of the prince of darknes; will he refuse to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue our bodies from the rage of the king of Spaine and his adherents, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when for the maintaining of his glorie, we shall not be afraid to expose the same vnto the edge of the sword?</p>
                  <p>It is no doubt a great comfort vnto a childe, to consider that he hath a father that loueth and cherisheth him, that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly careth for him, that prouideth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries for his maintenance; but let the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:13276:78"/> father loue his sonne neuer so much, let him leaue his son neuer so great wealth; yet is he not certain either of his fathers life for the continuance of this comfort, or of the substance which shall be left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, bicause although this father may frankly bequeath his goods to his sonne, yet can he not by any prerogatiue or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest he hath therein, make such assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as the same shall not be subiect to losse, change, and corruption: it is far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise with our heauenlie father, and with the inheritance of all the blessings which he bestoweth, we are sure neuer to be destitute of a father, bicause he is <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 1. 8. 11.</note> nor of a good father, bicause he is <hi>mercifull and of great kindnes,</hi> nor of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral <note place="margin">Ioel. 2. 13.</note> blessings, bicause he can both giue and assure them; nor of spirituall bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings, bicause they are laid vp for vs in his treasurie, where no man can take them from vs. Earthlie fathers will hazard far for their children, and labor to rid them out of their troubles, to protect them in their extremities, &amp; to furnish them with such necessaries as make for their defēce; but they cannot giue them anie assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their deliuerance; they can but
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:13276:78"/> minister the meanes, not promise suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse; bicause they themselues depend of a superior power: It were great arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for them, and an ouerweening pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption to proceed so far; but the Lord both can, and will performe all these things vnto vs: and therefore what shall make vs afraid? Shall the malice of the Spaniard? Shal the multitude and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this blood-thirstie tirant? Shall his great preparations, his threats, his brags, his weapons, nay his presence mooue vs? No, we are the Lords <note n="*" place="margin">Deu. 14. 1.</note> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and <note n="*" place="margin">Psal. 61. 4.</note>
                     <hi>vnder the shadow of his wings shall we be safe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He toucheth a tender thing that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the apple of our eie, and we haue reason to be carefull to saue the same harmeles, bicause of the necessarie vses thereof in this life; we are to the Lorde as the <hi>apple of his eie,</hi> according to his <note place="margin">Zach. 2. 8.</note> own testimonie, and he may easely iudge in what price and estimation we are with him, that wil consider what account and reckoning we make of this member: As we take him for our enimie that offereth violence vnto it; so do we straightway la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor by al good meanes to defend &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:13276:79"/> the same. The Lord dealeth in like maner, but vseth a more seuere kinde of proceeding; he doth not onely repute them his enimies that offerre violence vnto the apple of his eie, but also those that do but in any iniurious sort touch the same; and he doth not alone defend it from the violence and harme offered, but doth likewise take sharpe reuenge of the enimie.</p>
                  <p>Againe, we are the <hi>sheepe of that good shepheard</hi> whose eie is alwaies fixed vpon <note place="margin">Psal. 23. 1. Iohn 11. 14.</note> vs, who is carefull to feed, and to defend vs from the iawes of those rauenous beasts which lie in waite to deuour vs; if we go astraie, he is readie to bring vs home; if we fall into any danger, he is at hand to deliuer vs; if we are in any extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, he is present to helpe and assist vs, so as no ill can happen to those that are of his flocke. The good shepheard ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the safetie of his sheepe hath a fold to shut them vp from the violence of the sauage and bloodie woolfe; the Lorde hath more then folds; he hath strong forts to couer and shield vs, from the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saults of al Spanish woolues that prepare snares for our liues. The good shepheard
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:13276:79"/> attentiuely watcheth ouer his sheepe, but the weaknes of his flesh will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to be alwaies waking, for nature requireth somtimes to be refreshed, that it may be the better enabled to endure, and holde out; but the Lorde is not as man, he giueth himselfe no rest, <hi>He that keepeth Israell neither slumbreth nor sleepeth:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 121. 4.</note> he hath no need of this interchange, but sitteth in heauen, as in a watch-tower, and ouerseeth with an indefatigable care and diligence all his creatures, and with an especiall protection defendeth his chosen sheepe: and shal we then be afraid of a Spaniard?</p>
                  <p>Againe, we are soldiers of a most migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie captaine, and haue giuen our names <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2. 3.</note> to serue in his battels; he hath mustered vs, &amp; allowed vs in his field. A good cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine so much tendreth the conseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his soldiers, as he accounteth the disgrace, iniurie, and dommage done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, a great dishonor vnto himselfe, and will studie by all meanes to secure them from all danger: he will not spare his blood for their safetie, he will be the first to incourage them, and giue them an example to performe actions of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:13276:80"/> and chiualrie, and rather die before them, than staine his name with that foule and deepe-die of cowardice and infamie. If these worldly captaines haue such carefull consideration of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and of the conseruation of their sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: how much more carefull is the Lord of hosts to defend such as are in his pay; if the one thinke himselfe disgraced if the enimy insult and triumph ouer any of his soldiers, and studie to reuenge the same: how much more will that grand-captaine be reuenged for the disgrace, dishonor, and violence which shall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto those that are of his partie? And shall we then be afraide of a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard?</p>
                  <p>Thus are we (I meane the godly of our land) the sonnes of a most louing father, the apple of the Lords eie, the sheepe of a good shepheard, the soldiers of a puissant captaine, which last point giueth vs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the seconde consideration, namely, vnder whose banner and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct we fight. It is already sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared that the Lorde is our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; then it appeereth also that we fight vnder his conduct; in whom may be
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:13276:80"/> considered two speciall things, the one, <hi>that he is omnipotent,</hi> and therefore able to <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1. &amp; 35. 11.</note> lend his faithfull soldiers of England as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, able to stand for them, and to giue them strength to do valiant things: the other, <hi>that he is louing and mercifull;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioel 2. 13.</note> and therefore willing to receiue those that maintaine his cause, into his protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to giue vs all good meanes to withstand these Spanish enimies. That he is omnipotent, besides his owne testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie in Genesis, the creation of all the creatures celestiall and terrestrial do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it; their perpetuall conseruation and continued course since the beginning doth shew it; but these are things of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite consideration, exceeding the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of earth and ashes; the least worme, the least member and part of our bodie doth without exception confirme it. When we looke vpon our hand; the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viewe thereof giueth sufficient cause to admire the omnipotencie of the maker, and when we call to minde what rare things are performed by this only mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whether in matter of acts and scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or in any other arts of honor and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; we haue occasion thereby to enter
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:13276:81"/> into consideration of the mightie hand of that great workeman which made the same. If our hand of flesh is able through him to do these great things, how much more able is his owne hande to do the greatest? If his hand haue that power of nothing to create all things: how much more hath it power to defend that which he hath created? The prophet <hi>Esay</hi> saith, <note place="margin">Esay. 40. 12.</note> that <hi>he hath measured the waters with his fist, and counted heauen with a span, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the dust of the earth in a measure, &amp; waighed the mountaines in a waight, and the hils in a ballance. The Lord your God,</hi> (saith Moses) <hi>is God of Gods, and Lord of Lords, a</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 17</note>
                     <hi>great GOD, mightie, and terrible.</hi> There are infinite places in Scripture, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the infinite power of the Lord is set foorth vnto vs. And although the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the wicked doe make proofe that they haue wholie forgotten God: yet am I perswaded that as the verie diuell <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 8. 44.</note> their father doth beleeue and tremble, as it is in Saint <hi>Iames</hi> Epistle: so the <hi>Atheists</hi> of this age are not ignorant <note place="margin">Iames. 2. 19</note> that there is a God; a God of great power, might, and maiesty; and no doubt the cruell Spaniard, if he haue any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:13276:81"/> at al, is not without some feeling, that this God looketh into these his treacherous and blooddie resolutions; and that there remaineth a iudgement without mercie for him, who without all compassion hath alreadie in the lowe Countries, and is now also prepared to bath his butcherly sword in the pretious blood of his Saints in England. But let him know, that without this God, the best strength of man is nothing but weaknes; all his force nothing but infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; his speares, like bulrushes; his bucklers, like paper leaues; his bulwarks like heaps of snow against the sun, easily beaten down and consumed: and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the armies of the wicked be in number so many, as by them al the riuers of a country may be made dry; the moū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains plaines, and the plains mountains; though <hi>Pelion</hi> were laid vpon <hi>Ossa;</hi> the <hi>Alpes</hi> vpon the <hi>Riphean</hi> hils; and one vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, euen with those rebellious grants to wage battell against the Lord of hosts and his saints; though <hi>Babel</hi> tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers touch the clouds, and be made as a ladder to presumptuous <hi>Nimrod</hi> to scale <note place="margin">Genes. 11.<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> the wals of heauen; yet the least blast of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:13276:82"/> the Lords mouth is able to batter them downe, and to make them leuell with the earth; for it is not with our God as it is with the sonnes of men. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test and most puissant prince that liueth cannot vndertake anie enterprise offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siue or defensiue, but with the assistance either of his owne subiects, or helpe of confederate princes, and yet with all his helps, hath cause to stand in doubt of the issue and successe, bicause as he saith; <hi>Anceps est alea belli:</hi> The chance of war is doubtfull, or rather as the prophet spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth; <hi>Vaine is the helpe of man.</hi> But our <note place="margin">Psal. 60. 11.</note> God <hi>Iehoua</hi> needeth no mans helpe; all things are <hi>of him, through him, and for him:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 36</note> and although all the men of the world shall refuse to ioin with his saints in their godlie battels, or shall ioine togither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them: yet wil he arm the woorms and least things of the earth to take their part, and make them executioners of his iustice, wherof are extāt in * <hi>Pharao,</hi> in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 8. Acts. 12. 23. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Mac. 9. 9.</note> in * <hi>Antiochus,</hi> in many others notable examples; nay he will adde such strength to the hand of his people, that <hi>Shamgar</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ud. 3. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rledge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udg. 15. 15.</note> shall pearce the sides of sixe hundred of the vncircumcised with a goade; * <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:13276:82"/> shal slaie a thousand with a iawebone; <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17. 49.</note>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> kill <hi>Goliah</hi> with a sling, to the vtter discouragement and confusion of all Philistins; one man shall ouercome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, one hundred a thousand, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sande a million of enimies; nay he will giue power to the sounde of a horne or trumpet to throw downe the wals of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo,</hi> to ouerthrow the gates and fences <note place="margin">Iosua. 6. 20.</note> of the strongest cities, he will with <hi>Moses</hi> rod deuide the sea, and make a path for his chosen people, but ouerwhelme <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exo. 14. 21. 23. 27.</note> and all the obstinate <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> with the waues thereof. But (which is most woonderfull) he sheweth his mightie power sometimes without these visible meanes, being able to kill the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious generation with the breath of his mouth, &amp; to make the wicked feele the blow, but not see the hande, or weapon that strooke them, to the ende they should haue his mightie power in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter admiration, and learne to intreat his children with more lenitie and charitie. The guiltie conscience of the wicked is in steede of an armie against himselfe, who as <hi>Salomon</hi> saith, <hi>fleeth when no man</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 1.</note>
                     <hi>pursueth him:</hi> within, he feeleth terrors,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:13276:83"/> which giue him no rest; without, he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the shaking of euerie leafe, which taketh away his courage; he imagineth that he heareth the trampling of horses, the noise of charets, and sound of a great <note place="margin">2. King. 7. 6.</note> armie, as did the <hi>Aramites,</hi> which meanes the Lord vsed for a defence of his people of Israell; thus I saie shall the enimies of Gods children flee, although no man force them, they shall fall although no man touch them, yea they shall fall, and neuer rise againe, for the Lord shall <hi>tread them vnder his feete,</hi> and crush them in <note place="margin">Psal. 60. 12.</note> peeces. It is a good incouragement to a soldier, if in a conflict he hath gotten but some small aduantage of his enimie; but to hold him captiue vnder him, is a far greater comfort, bicause he hath escaped the present danger wherevnto he was subiect during that doubtfull fight; but his feare is suddenly renued by a fresh assault, he hath not so soone rid him selfe of one enimie, but he falleth into the hands of another, and so is there a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall succession of dangers: but the Lord is able at once to confound them al, and in a moment to secure his, frō al peril, by treading of whole armies vnder his feet.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:13276:83"/> Heerby it appeereth that victories stand not simplie in the multitude of warriors, in the arme of flesh, the strength of forts, the force of munitions, the sharpenes of weapons, the skilfulnes of captaines, the aduantage of ground, and such like, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though these are sometimes meanes to obtaine great victories:) for then could <hi>Dauid</hi> neuer haue so long escaped the cruell hands of persecuting <hi>Saul,</hi> and of the bloodie <hi>Philistins;</hi> nor the <hi>Israelites,</hi> so often haue beene deliuered from the innumerable troupes of their enimies; neither had it beene possible for <hi>Gedeon</hi> with three hundred men, to ouercome the whole huge host of the <hi>Midianites.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 22.</note> Manie like examples occur in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I leaue to the better remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and due consideration of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Reader.</p>
                  <p>And as the Lord is a mightie captaine and protector, so is he no lesse mercifull, willing, and at hand to all that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course vnto him <hi>Cast all your care vpon him</hi> (saith <hi>Peter) for he eareth for you:</hi> if he be <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 7.</note> carefull of vs, then is he no doubt willing to expresse the same towards vs, whereof the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> giueth sufficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:13276:84"/> who of all men had best experience of his willing carefulnes, and careful wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes to deliuer him, euen in despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate extremities. The testimonies heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are plentifull in his Psalmes, yea (such was his thankfulnes) almost in euerie Psalme, and the examples of his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from manifold dangers are very rife in other parts of scripture. The om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie and willingnes of the Lord, in the preseruation of his people, do so concur togither, as by the particularities hath alreadie appeered; as I shall not need any further to inlarge this second point.</p>
                  <p>Then let vs learne to depend of the mightie power and willing assistance of our God; let vs be strong and couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in him; let vs not <hi>be afraid what man</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 56. 4.</note>
                     <hi>can do vnto vs;</hi> let vs apply our selues to make vp the breaches of our state, and to strengthen our part by the best meanes which the Lord hath presented vnto vs; they are not to be neglected: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did not like vnto <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib,</hi> trust vnto his arme of flesh, yet <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chro. 32. <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 6.</note> we read that he <hi>built all the broken wals of Iudah, and made vp the towers, and repaired</hi>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:13276:84"/>
                     <hi>Millo in the citie of Dauid, and made manie darts and shields, and set captaines of war ouer the people:</hi> adding words of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment woorthie a godlie and zealous Prince, to animate them to fight the Lords battel, wherein he had a very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie successe, as appeereth in scripture.</p>
                  <p>We cannot build vp towers, repaire breaches, prepare munitions, intertaine captaines and soldiers without liberall contributions; and therefore wee must forget our old vaine of sparing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to open our bags, which haue beene so long shut, and poure out with a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull hand our coine for our defence. Spending in this case is sparing; but ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly pinching, cause of losse neuer to be recouered. We labor too much of this dangerous disease of heaping togither of wealth, by the which, vnles we shal be cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to purge our coffers with a more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral hand to be extended to the wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seruing soldier, &amp; to the former necessary purposes; the body of our state is like to be greatly endangered. In our pompe &amp; delicacies, in our shewes and triumphes, to set foorth our owne glorie, or rather vanitie; we stick at no costs nor charges:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:13276:85"/> and shal we be niggards, wholie deuoted and wedded to our bags, when our liues, when our land, when religion, when Gods cause is to be defended? Shall we reserue in our coffers, as it were swords to cut our owne throats? Shall we make so much of mammon, as God shall be neglected? O the foolish and dangerous loue of riches and treasure! O the vaine and vnprofitable care of our profits!</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Ladies for the preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their citie, refused not to throwe their most pretious iewels into that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping gulfe: but manie of vs will hardlie depart with our basest coine to saue a whole realme. They, when the treasurie was through long and continuall wars reduced to great necessitie, could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, after atchieued victories, to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute liberally good store of their richest gems, towards the making of a huge Crowne to be consecrated to their god <hi>Apollo:</hi> but manie of vs are so far, either to conserue religion, or to serue the true GOD with our richest things; as we grudge to bestow a little portion of our meanest substance to these purposes. Did superstitious deuotion mooue them to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:13276:85"/> performe these actions of honor and bountie; and shall we neither in godlie discretion duly regard, nor in holie and sound religion, make estimation of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and religious contributions? How slenderly many do it, euidently appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: when there is question of some good course to be taken for the better aduancing of martiall seruices; do not the most extenuate their sufficiency, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend losses, alledge desperate dets, and diuers other excuses, bicause they would auoid liberall expence in these causes? bicause they would spare that with mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablenes, for the which they afterward make themselues miserable? Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that this is an vsuall practise with worldlings? But these men seeking to deceiue others, may finde themselues most of all deceiued in the end. The sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier hazardeth his life; spendeth his blood; looseth his lims; is parched with heate; pinched with cold; fareth hard; sleepeth little; exposeth himselfe to all extremities: yet will they not regarde him, vnles extremitie inforce them? And in extremitie who but the soldier? But if the danger and feare be once ouerpast;
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:13276:86"/> well is he somtimes rewarded, that es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capeth without disgrace. Howbeit this must not discomfort vs: the cause of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion giueth incouragement; the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces safetie giueth incouragement; the countries weale giueth incouragement; and euerie mans particular giueth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement: religion, the prince, the countrie, the people, yea euerie particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man is interessed in this action. Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace must not daunt, nor feare discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, nor danger deter, nor the illiberall dealing of the couetous, cause valiant captaines, soldiers, and other good sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to faint or quaile in these so hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, religious, and godlie resolutions: and yet I would to God that the close-handed worldlings would be as forward to contribute to their defence, as they are willing to be defended.</p>
                  <p>This liberalitie and carefulnes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and strengthen our selues, are verie good helps, and a stop to stay the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the threatening <hi>Spaniard;</hi> these are instruments wherewith the Lord of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten brideleth the rage of those that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose themselues against his children. The wicked abuse them to offend vs, then let
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:13276:86"/> vs vse them to defend our selues against their bloodie inuasions. It incourageth an enimie greatly, when he vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that there are weake places in the land, wherof he desireth to make a pray; nay somtimes it maketh an enimie, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition easily findeth occasion of quarrel: and it is an vsuall practise of inuaders, to learne what coasts are most easie to be assaulted; in what part of the citie a breach may soonest be made; where he may most fitly plant his battell, giue the batterie, and get the conquest. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> is wilie, let vs be warie; he is po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike; let vs be prudent; he armeth, let vs take our weapons; he prepareth, let vs not be founde vnreadie; he procureth helps from his ghostly father and others of that confederacie, let vs not be negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent (if neede require) to craue the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of such as haue a part in the good or bad successe of our defensiue forces: if he come not, or comming haue not such successe as he already promiseth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himselfe, let vs not feare to visite his coasts; the issue of former honorable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprises giueth great hope of like, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better euent. The Gospell is nowe
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:13276:87"/> interessed; the malice was before mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with pretences, nowe it is broken out, and is apparant that first, the extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of religion is sought, then the subuersion of the state of our sacred prince and countrie. Thus is it the Lords owne cause, and we shal fight his battels, and therefore let vs be no lesse strong, than couragious in him: which is a part of <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> exhortation to his people, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Chr. 32. 7</note> and a second helpe to withstand the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: <hi>Though ten thousand</hi> (saith Dauid) <note place="margin">Psal. 3. 6.</note>
                     <hi>shoulde hem me in, yet woulde I not be afraide.</hi> There can be no greater enimie to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable actions, than pusillanimity; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in a little bodie (I meane true forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) feareth not to encounter with gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, and not to haue great lims, but a good hart, atchieueth victories. We shall seldome reade or heare of any woorthie enterprise performed by a timorous sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier; feare turneth the backe at the least dangers, courage opposeth it selfe to all hazards; feare argueth for the most part the badnes of the cause, courage sheweth that it standeth with right, and is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with honor: and as courage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie doe vsually accompanie ech
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:13276:87"/> other; so feare and guiltines are seldome separated. The heathen had nothing in greater estimation than to eternize their names by glorious actions, and for this purpose haue thought no danger too great, nor exploit too hard; they haue not spared their goods, their blood, their liues to perform such enterprises as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased honor. But some doubt may be made whether they were more desperate and presumptuous, than valiant and couragious. <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> plaied the part of a valiant <hi>Romain,</hi> but not of a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian: and yet in that <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> so reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, or rather so desperately leaped in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gulfe for the safegard of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and to preserue the same from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger; teacheth Christians, not so desperately as he did, but more reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely than in former times they haue done, to take vpon them by all good meanes, with due regard of the preserua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their liues, the protection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their countrey. He that wil look into the histories of former times shall finde manie rare examples of couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous captaines, to whom nothing was so pretious and deere as their countrey. But
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:13276:88"/> seeing that not onely our Countrey, but also the most pretious and inestimable iewell of the word, is at once to be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and preserued among vs: our pusil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanimitie shall be ouer-great, nay it shall be imputed vnto vs for a sinne, if we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not, and proceed like most Christian captaines to this combate. Thus seruile feare being banished, we shall finde in vs a forceable resolution, and resolute per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion, which will draw vs forwarde in this our martiall course; such as was in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who to his great incouragement spake it, and to our comfort hath left it enregistred in his booke of Psalmes: <note place="margin">Psal. 60. 12.</note>
                     <hi>Through God we shall do valiantly;</hi> which resolution, appeereth to haue proceeded from a firme and constant faith in the Lord. It is not mixed with any ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or doubtfull termes, it is not groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, vpon hap-hazard; he saith not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps we shall, but absolutely <hi>we shall do valiantly.</hi> The wauering, irresolute and faint hart in good causes, findeth manie difficulties to staie the course of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; euerie trifle deterreth him to put in execution any religious and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable enterprise; the smallest crosse
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:13276:88"/> maketh him to despaire of successe in his actions; but such as set vp their rest on the assistance of the God of <hi>Israel, Iehoua</hi> strong and mightie, resolue to oppose themselues against all euents, to swallow all inconueniences, and to persist euen with delight &amp; pleasure in their paineful course, which promiseth a happy issue to the Church of God and their Countrey.</p>
                  <p>We haue (God be thanked for it) embraced this present occasion for our defence, (as it seemeth) resolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: nothing else can encourage the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to vndertake that which he hath threatened, or (if he nowe misse of his purpose) to prosecute the same hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; then our want of present expedition, then our future securitie, and remisse dealing when the storme shall seeme to be ouerpast; a matter meete to be obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and noted, bicause it threatneth and draweth therewith great dangers.</p>
                  <p>Haue we therefore resolutely taken our weapons in hande? Let vs not disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely lay them downe: haue we scoured our rustie corslets and halberds, which haue so long lien by the wals? Let vs not againe cast them into corners, but keepe
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:13276:89"/> them alwaies cleane and feruiceable: haue we practised anie feates of armes whereby we may be enhabled to meete a <hi>Spaniard</hi> in the field? Let vs exercise the same daily, and continue in this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of seruice: haue we beene neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent so many yeeres, and hath this sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den alarme rowzed vs from the bed of securitie? Let vs still be vigilant; least hereafter he come before he threat, and ouercome, before wee haue sufficient means to make resistance. For although the Lord watcheth for his <hi>Israel,</hi> yet must not <hi>Israel</hi> snort securely; but be vigilant <note place="margin">Psal. 121. 4.</note> to heare that great watchman when he calleth, and giueth vs warning of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger. In this resolution must all the members and subiects of the land ioyne togither: it sufficeth not that the greater part concur in this defensiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but there must be a mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, a correspondencie of affection, and they must be all as it were linked togither in one band. I am not ignorant that all drawe not one waie; that there are manie so much infected with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, as they stande verie ill affected to their prince, and hir more faithfull
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:13276:89"/> subiects; such as coulde (no doubt) be content to lende all their assistaunce to the enimie, if any fit opportunitie were presented: which thing, their manifold treacherous practises woonderfully dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, do sufficiently witnes. Ouer these, it shall be very needfull, and shall make much for our securitie, as to haue a vigilant eie, so to carie a seuere and straight hand. They deale secretly; they practise in the darke; they conspire in corners; and therefore must bee well looked vnto: they are head-strong; they will not be ordered by law; they exempt themselues from their subiection and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to their naturall prince; and therefore their insolencie requireth a strong snaffle: otherwise it will proceed verie far, to the indangering, or at the least endammaging of our present state. How they may be reduced to some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter order, otherwise than by force I see not; and yet howsoeuer they are persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Spanish fauor, in that they are <hi>Catholiks</hi> and weare his badge: I doubt he would scarse acknowledge them to be of his partie, although by their helpe he might obtaine his purpose: for as the
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:13276:90"/>
                     <hi>Spaniard</hi> is feruent in his blind religion; so is he also insolent, couetous, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, and would first seeke the satisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of his aspiring mind, by the Crown: then, of his couetous and reuenging hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, by a generall spoile; or if any fared the better, it is likely he would prefer his own nation: and experience hath taught vs, that this people do hardly brooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other partner in any thing, whereof they onely may enioy the benefite and commoditie. This also may be fitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered, that in a generall conquest, the soldier carrieth a greater respect to the bootie, than to religion; that, is the first thing he regardeth; this, shal be thought vpon at better leasure. Our Papists are full, and possesse more riches than they well vse; they haue manie heapes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; manie faire houses; manie pleasant places; or rather pallaces, which would easilye inuite a <hi>Spaniard</hi> to cut their throats; and they would not faile to do it, and to say afterwards, that they tooke them for <hi>Huguenots;</hi> or else they would say with <hi>Antigonus; Proditionem amo, non proditores:</hi> I like the treason, but not the traitor; so should they receiue a traitors
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:13276:90"/> hire. Thus is there cause why the Papists should also ioine with vs, in good polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, howsoeuer they dissent in true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But it is likely, that fearing some har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der measure than hath hitherto beene vsed towards them, they shew some bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conformitie in this time of triall; and it may be that they also contribute libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to this and the like seruices: neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles their treacherous and seditious disposition deserueth to be alwaies had in suspition; for it is impossible at once to be friends with that presumptuous Prelate, and with our liege Soueraigne, whose supremacie and prerogatiue can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in one land stand both togither. But if the children of God shall with one faith, with one hart and hand hold fast togither, the children of <hi>Belial</hi> shall fall, and come to vtter confusion.</p>
                  <p>Now these externall meanes haue not alwaies their wished successe, least man should ascribe victorie vnto them; and therefore godlie pollicie and praier must go togither, that the one may be holpen by the other: when that faileth; this, is a present defence, and helpe will arriue beyond all hope. <hi>Some put their trust in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 20. 7.</note>
                     <pb n="168" facs="tcp:13276:91"/>
                     <hi>chariots</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid) and some in horses; but we wil remember the name of the Lord.</hi> When our armies are dispersed; our wals razed; our speares shiuered; our bulwarks bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; the enimie behind vs; the sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs; mountaines on ech side; and no way to escape the sword; yet at <hi>Moises</hi> praier, the Lord will diuide the waters, and giue his <hi>Israel</hi> free passage, when <hi>Pharao</hi> with all his host shal perish and be ouerwhelmed: which giueth vs this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, that although the <hi>Spanish Pharao</hi> were alreadie landed; entred into the field; had giuen vs battell; and were pursuing vs at our heeles: yet if we faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call vpon the Lord, he will not giue vs ouer into his bloody hands; according to his owne promise; <hi>Call vpon me in the time of trouble, and I wil deliuer thee, and thou</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 50. 15.</note>
                     <hi>shalt glorifie me.</hi> If we will be heard, we must call, and that not faintly, but ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly, and without intermission. In that hot conflict of the children of <hi>Israel</hi> with the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> so long as <hi>Moises</hi> held vp <note place="margin">Exod. 17. 11</note> his hands and praied, the <hi>Israelites</hi> had the best, but when he let them fall, the aduerse part preuailed; so as <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> were forced to sustaine the weaknes
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:13276:91"/> of his arms: a sufficient example to shew that the Lord will not be called vpon by halfs, or by fits, or for a fashion, or as our owne humor shall mooue vs, or present necessitie inforce vs; but hee requireth continuall supplications, voluntarie and hartie praier, with indefatigable lifting vp of hands to the throne of his maiesty, from whence commeth helpe, agreeable with that wholsom admonition of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his 6. chapter to the Ephesians; <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 18.</note>
                     <hi>Praie alwaies with all maner praier and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in the spirit, and watch thereunto with all perseuerance for all saints.</hi> The patient that desireth to escape any dangerous disease, will open his griefe to the skilfull Physition, and earnestly craue his helpe for the speedie cure thereof, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie this; but (which agreeth with our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose) he will daily and howerly (if it be required) applie his wholsom medicins. The like is to be done in our desperate extremities, nay in the least dangers: we must vse praier to the Lord, as the sicke patient vseth the phisitions prescripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which is a meane and medicine to preserue vs from all perill, not of bodie onely, but also of soule. But we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:13276:92"/> sicke, and haue need of helpe; we are continually exposed to manie ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards and mischiefes, especially if we be the children of God, and haue an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest deuotion to serue him. Enimies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, enimies at home, forren enimies, domesticall enimies, open enimies, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret enimies, yea swarmes of both sorts; chiefely such as will fleere in our faces, and wish for oportunitie to cutte our throates; such as haue honie in their mouths, and gall in their harts; such as like <hi>Iudas</hi> dip their sop with vs in our <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 23.</note> dishes, when they haue conspired and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued to betraie Christ with vs, and vs with Christ; such as enter into our Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues like the <hi>Pharisies,</hi> into our chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and congregations like the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> when indeed they abhor vs and our religion: whose praiers are not for the state of the true church, for the propagation of the Gospell, for the safetie of the Prince and people; but for the setting vp of idolatrie, for the resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the masse, for the vtter extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word of the Lord, and subuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the present state of the land. But notwithstanding this their malice, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:13276:92"/> all the Spanish trecheries: our God saith, that if we call vpon him, he will heare vs, and not onely heare, but also deliuer vs from the iawes of these sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage blood-suckers. Though we see no helpe, yet will he open our eies, and we shall finde our selues inuironed with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of angels to whom he hath giuen charge of our safetie: <hi>Elishas</hi> seruant shall <note place="margin">Psal. 91. 11. 2. King. 6. 17</note> see troupes of horses and chariots of fire attending vpon his master and him; <hi>Elias</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Kings 1. 10, 12.</note> shall command fire from heauen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume the soldiers of wicked <hi>Ahaziah;</hi> and at the praier of distressed <hi>Dauid, The earth shall tremble and quake, the foundations</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psalm. 18. 7, 8, 9.</note>
                     <hi>of the mountains shall mooue and shake bicause of the Lords anger, smoke shall go out of his nostrels, and a consuming fire out of his mouth; coales shall be kindled thereat; He will bowe the heauens also and come downe, and darknes shall be vnder his feete, &amp;c.</hi> Thus will the Lord shewe himselfe vnto our enimies, thus will he stand by vs, and fight for vs, if we crie and call vnto him. But we must remember this, that as he is gratious to deliuer vs, so he expecteth thanks at our hands for this deliuerance; we must glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him, we must extoll his name, and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:13276:93"/> acknowledge his great goodnes for our preseruation. If we confer but a slender benefite vpon any man whatsoeuer, we would esteeme him verie ingratefull if he should faile in the dutie of thankefulnes; yea we would looke for some requitall vpon any iust occasion offered: much more ought we to performe all thankful offices towards our good God, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth no other rewarde at our hands, than the onely acknowledgement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and whose benefits towards vs, are daily infinite, and without number.</p>
                  <p>Now it shal be good for vs to examine our selues how we haue beene affected for the great fauors past, for so manie yeeres peace vnder our gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, for such manifold and rare bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of quietnes and plentie, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his word so plentifully preached among vs, which no nation vnder the sunne hath enioied so long, nor so libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; neither can it be remembred that any people euer went before vs for these temporall things, nor that any countrey is more happie for this spirituall iewell. Let vs looke vpon our neighbors of ech side: The lowe countries are as it were
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:13276:93"/> deuoured by the <hi>Spaniard:</hi> The <hi>French</hi> troubled with ciuill dissentions, and the Gospell much eclipsed in these parts with the darke cloudes of superstition: neither hath the busie <hi>Spaniard</hi> beene long free from the Turkish forces; a iust measure for his vniust and tyrannous dealing with Gods children, and he hath cause to feare (God turne awaie this great mishap from Christendome for his Christs sake) that without repentance, the cruel <hi>Turke</hi> wil deale with him as did <hi>Q. Tomiris</hi> with <hi>Cyrus:</hi> fill his mouth with blood being dead, who is neuer satisfied therewith aliue. Thus are our neighbors tossed on ech side, and we in great secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and safetie; and are our fruits an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to this great happines? Is our deuotion the more feruent? Do we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his word with that zeale which he requireth in the worde? Many do it no doubt with great sinceritie, but the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the most is apparant. But if we desire the continuance of Gods fauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able countenance towards vs, we must ioyne togither in this dutie aboue all things, which is the principall meane to make him ioyne with vs. If this long
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:13276:94"/> time of peace hath made vs careles ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; let vs now put on a better affection towards the same; if the plentie of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall bread hath made vs to loath that spirituall manna, let vs now feede more hungerlie thereon: if the riches and wealth of this worlde haue choaked vs, and made vs to forget the treasures of that heauenly <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> let vs now more studiouslie and earnestly seeke after that precious pearle which is in the treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the most highest. God hath loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for it at our handes manie yeeres; hee hath waited for better fruites with great patience from the barren trees of <hi>England,</hi> which hee euen nowe threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth <note place="margin">Matt. 3. 10.</note> to hewe downe, and cast into the fire, vnlesse they foorth-with become fruitful. He hath long spared them at the earnest intreatie of the gardeners; that is, for his faithfull ministers, and for his <note place="margin">Luke. 13. 8.</note> elects sake: and <hi>Sodom</hi> fareth the better bicause of righteous <hi>Lot</hi> and his familie. And this may bee the comfort of the godlie of this land, that the Lord wil not giue them and theirs into the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hands, but will spare <hi>Sodom</hi> at <hi>Abrahams</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 32.</note> request, if there may be but ten righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:13276:94"/> found therein. I hope <hi>England</hi> is not yet come to that excesse of wickednes, but that there are manie <hi>Lots</hi> among vs: and not onely ten, but ten thousand of sound &amp; religious professors, for whose sake the Lord will forbeare to execute his iust wrath, and to take reuenge vpon such as haue forsaken him. And yet it may bee truly affirmed, which a graue Doctor and learned minister of Christ hath lately pronounced; <hi>The greatest eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of England, are the sins of England:</hi> and one onelie sinne is able to do vs more hurt, than a thousand Spaniards. But as the former example giueth a generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to all the godlie: so may that example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> causing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Israel</hi> to be numbred, giue vs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that we trust not to our numbers; that we desire not to know our strength to presume of the same: for <hi>Dauids</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption cost the liues of three-score <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24. 15.</note> and ten thousand of his subiects. And if we offend in the like fault; shal we looke to escape like punishment? No; he will if not with the Spanish sword, yet with his owne rod, correct and chastise such intollerable presumption.</p>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:13276:95"/>
                  <p> The Lord for his mercie grant, that our sins make not a separation betwixt vs and him; nothing els can do it; none but our selues and our sins can betray vs into the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hands; he may exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise vs for a time; he may giue him leaue to threaten vs, to assault vs, and to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs; but he wil not suffer him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer vs, bicause he is insolent; nor to raigne ouer vs, bicause he is a tyrant; nor to reduce this realme to so misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a seruitude, bicause he is a superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous insolent tyrant, who seeketh to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the kingdome of <hi>Christ</hi> and his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to the vsurping power of that proud <hi>Antichrist;</hi> but especially bicause of the couenant which hee hath made from the beginning with his faithfull and chosen people, (which couenant shal stand for euer:) that is, that he will be <hi>our God,</hi> our <hi>Sauior,</hi> our <hi>Protector</hi> for euer. To this God, Sauior, and Protector, be praise and glorie now and for euer.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:13276:95"/>
            <head>Faults escaped.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 11. line. 3. read greater.</item>
               <item>Pag. 12. line. 9. read blinded.</item>
               <item>Pag. 34. line. 25. read than a gesse.</item>
               <item>Pag. 107. line. 8. read in the prouerb.</item>
               <item>Pag. 139. line. 25. read against.</item>
               <item>Pag. 142. line. 6. read although a father.</item>
               <item>Pag. 147. line. 26. read arts.</item>
               <item>Pag. 147. line. 27. read acts.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>